<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unhappy kindness, or, A fruitless revenge a tragedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal / wrirten [sic] by Mr. Scot.</title>
            <author>Scott, Mr. (Thomas), fl. 1696-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2089B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17215173</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17215173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58829)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1100:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unhappy kindness, or, A fruitless revenge a tragedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal / wrirten [sic] by Mr. Scot.</title>
                  <author>Scott, Mr. (Thomas), fl. 1696-1697.</author>
                  <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625. Wife for a month.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 58 [i.e. 48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Rhodes ... S. Briscoe ... and R. Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An alteration of Fletcher's A wife for a month.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. numbers 41-50 omitted.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Vnhappy Kindneſs:</hi> OR A Fruitleſs Revenge.</p>
            <p>A TRAGEDY, As it is Acted at the Theatre Royal.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Ad Generum Cereris ſine caede, &amp; ſanguine pauci Deſcendunt Reges.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juv. Sat. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Wrirten by Mr. <hi>SCOT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet, S. Briſcoe</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> and <hi>R. Parker</hi> at the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <div type="publishers_advertisement">
               <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
               <p>THere is now in the Preſs, and will be ſpeedily publiſhed a Collection of Familiar Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on ſeveral occaſions. Written by the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> late Earl of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> the Honourable <hi>Algern. Sydnys</hi> Letter concerning Bribery and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and Mr. <hi>Otways</hi> Love Letters written to a Lady. Publiſhed from their Original Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies. Printed for <hi>Sam. Briſcoe</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AMongſt a number of New Plays that of late have crowded the Stage, I thought an old Subject, tho for no other account than the Reſpect we are for the moſt part apt to pay Antiquity, might meet with ſome Civility; this was lookt on by ſome, well vers'd in the Rules and Beauties of Poetry, as a Piece that wou'd not be altogether unacceptable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it appeared with a new Air more agreeable to the Humour of the preſent Age. 'Tis true, I found my ſelf deceived in the working it up, and perceiv'd it requir'd more labour than I at firſt deſign'd it; for what with making ſome Characters entirely new, and reforming others, I found by that time I had done, I had little or none remaining but the Deſign: As it is, it may bear up in the Winter, notwithſtanding the little Encouragement it met with at its firſt appearance from a thin Town, and the Scarcity of Money. I muſt own the Town has been very favourable to Me, and they who found nothing to commend, thought not fit to condemn what was writ purely for their Diverſion. 'Tis true, every thing is not to be judg'd
<pb facs="tcp:106256:3"/>according to the Succeſs it meets with on the Stage; 'tis an eaſier Task to divert than pleaſe, foraſmuch as the firſt. like a ſudden flaſh, ſtrikes only on the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; whil'ſt the other is expoſed to the Severity of Judgment and Reaſon. <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Character in the laſt Act looks as if I had been reſolv'd, whatever Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities I committed, to make the Part for the Lines, and not the Lines for the Part, and therefore kill'd him in Oppoſition to a known Rule in Poetry: I am almoſt ready to confeſs it, tho, how far I have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſt therein let the Critick judge; if he is offended at his laſt Scene, let the reſt, which are all new, plead in my Behalf; I'm ſure it improv'd his Character, and, through the Excellence of the Action, appear'd very beautiful on the Stage. The laſt Scene in the Third Act had the Misfortune to offend ſome, who are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more curious than becomes either their Modeſty or good Manners; but that Man is in good hands, who has Pride and Affectation for his Judges.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Scot.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Spoken by Mr. <hi>Verbruggen.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I'M thinking, Sirs, how ſoon we are undone,</l>
            <l>Deſerted thus by the inconſtant Town.</l>
            <l>Where are thoſe Friends, that did in numerous throngs</l>
            <l>Crowd to our Muſick, and applaud our Songs?</l>
            <l>Curſe on this dull prepoſterous Soil! ſince all</l>
            <l>The Winter gave the Summer muſt recal;</l>
            <l>Tho more than <hi>Greenland</hi> Frosts prevail'd elſewhere,</l>
            <l>Yet then you found a warm Reception here,</l>
            <l>But now <hi>Hide-Park</hi> ſcarce yeilds ſo freſh an Air.</l>
            <l>Well then, we have reſolv'd, till your return,</l>
            <l>Since you, our Soveraigns, leave us, we'll adjourn;</l>
            <l>Only once more your Subjects humbly pray,</l>
            <l>You'd ſet your Hands to a few Acts to day;</l>
            <l>Some new, but made on purpoſe to unfold</l>
            <l>The meaning if the reſt, long ſince grown old,</l>
            <l>By your fam'd Anceſtors confirm'd to th' Stage</l>
            <l>In <hi>Fletcher</hi>'s time, the Muſes Golden Age:</l>
            <l>'Tis true, our Money may adulterate grow,</l>
            <l>But Wit muſt ſtill from one pure Fountain flow;</l>
            <l>Pull not the well-plac'd Lawrels from his Brow,</l>
            <l>What pleas'd them then, we hope will pleaſe you now.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:4"/>
            <head>The EPILOGUE written, and ſpoke, by Mr. <hi>Haynes,</hi> in the Habit of a <hi>Horſe Officer,</hi> mounted on an <hi>Aſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu have ſeen (before now) ſince this <hi>Shape-ſhewing age,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More Aſſes than mine, on a <hi>Beau-crowded</hi> Stage.</l>
               <l>Wherefore by th' Example of <hi>Fam'd Dogget,</hi> my Brother,</l>
               <l>To ſhew our Stage has Aſſes on't, as well as t' other;</l>
               <l>Thus mounted I'm come to invite ye oft hither,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Beaumont</hi> and <hi>Fletcher</hi> thus coupled together.</l>
               <l>My <hi>Fancy,</hi> his <hi>Judgment;</hi> my <hi>Perſon,</hi> his <hi>Face;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With the mighty <hi>Intereſt</hi> he has in this place,</l>
               <l>(For indeed, as I'm told, but pray let me not wrong ye).</l>
               <l>My Aſs has <hi>Relations,</hi> and Great ones among ye;</l>
               <l>In the Galleries, Side Boxes, on the Stage, in the Pit;</l>
               <l>What's your <hi>Critick?</hi> Your <hi>Beau?</hi> Your <hi>Keeper?</hi> Your <hi>Wit?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your <hi>Fighting</hi> Aſs is a <hi>Bully,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Sneaking</hi> Aſs is a <hi>Cit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Keeping</hi> Aſs is a <hi>Cully,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But your Top, <hi>Prime</hi> Aſs is your <hi>Wit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They all fool Cit of his Wife,</l>
               <l>He fools them all of their Pelf;</l>
               <l>But your <hi>Wit</hi>'s ſo damn'd an <hi>Aſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He only fools himſelf!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Writing one Play a Year, for a Wit he'd paſs,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Lean</hi> Third Day makes out to him he's an Aſs.</l>
               <l>Be'nt I an Aſs now thus to mount my <hi>Brother;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But he that's <hi>pleas'd</hi> with it too, is not he <hi>Another?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are we not Aſſes all (twixt me and you)</l>
               <l>To part with out <hi>Old Money</hi> till we were ſure of <hi>New?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since then ſo many Aſſes here abound,</l>
               <l>Where an Eternal Link of Wit goes round,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>No Poet ſure will think it a Diſgrace,</l>
               <l>To be ally'd to <hi>This Accompliſht</hi> Aſs,</l>
               <l>For he's a great <hi>Critick</hi> you may read it in his Face.</l>
               <l>As for his <hi>Courage</hi> truly I ca'nt ſay much,</l>
               <l>Yet he might ſerve for a <hi>Trooper</hi> among the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho, of their <hi>Side,</hi> Im ſure he'd never <hi>fight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> ſhews I'm in the right.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Whips the Aſs often, who by reaſon of the innate Dullneſs of the Beaſt never flnches for it.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>He's a Courtier fit to appear before a Queen;</l>
               <l>Advance <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> view but his Mein:</l>
               <l>Ladies, I'm ſure you like his ſpruce Behaviour,</l>
               <l>I ne'r knew ought but <hi>Aſſes</hi> in <hi>Their favour.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fair Ones,</hi> at what I ſay take no Offence!</l>
               <l>For—</l>
               <l>When his <hi>Degree</hi> a <hi>Lover</hi> does commence,</l>
               <l>You <hi>coin</hi> an <hi>Aſs</hi> out of a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Senſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Beaus</hi> that <hi>ſoften</hi> ſo your <hi>flinty</hi> Hearts,</l>
               <l>They are Aſſes— <hi>Taylors</hi> make them <hi>Men</hi> of Parts.</l>
               <l>Now ſome have told me this might give Offence,</l>
               <l>That <hi>riding</hi> my Aſs thus is <hi>riding</hi> th' Audience;</l>
               <l>But what of that? the <hi>Brother</hi> rides the <hi>Brother,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Son</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> we <hi>All</hi> ride one another:</l>
               <l>Then for a <hi>Jeſt</hi> for this time let it paſs,</l>
               <l>For he that <hi>takes it ill</hi> I'm <hi>Sure</hi>'s an Aſs.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:106256:5"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <head>MEN.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ALphonſo,</hi> King of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frederick,</hi> his Brother, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Valerio,</hi> a Noble <hi>Neapolitan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sorano, Frederick</hi>'s Creature.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Piſano, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uchio, Alphonſo</hi>'s Friends:</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> An old Officer.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Verbruggen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Harland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Diſney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mills.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Neuth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>EN.</head>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>other.</item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Rogers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Powel.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106256:5"/>
               <head>ACT I. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Sorano <hi>and</hi> Evanthe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sorano.</speaker>
                  <l>THus to adore, and thus to be rewarded,</l>
                  <l>Still to deſire, and ſtill deſire in vain;</l>
                  <l>Is there no end of all my Miſeries,</l>
                  <l>And of your cruel and ſevere Diſdain?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evanthe.</speaker>
                  <p>Alaſs! My Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you have eyes to wound;</l>
                  <l>Yet want thoſe eyes to ſee the wounds you make?</l>
                  <l>Why has Heav'n giv'n you Beauty to deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>And not a Heart to pity theſe you kill?</l>
                  <l>A long and tedious Service have I paid you;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n from your Childhood I have been your Slave,</l>
                  <l>Courted the earlieſt glories of your Youth</l>
                  <l>With the ſincereſt Love, before you was</l>
                  <l>To others known, by me you was ador'd.</l>
                  <l>Madam, I am —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>You are indeed my Lord</l>
                  <l>More than the niceſt gratitude can ſpeak you,</l>
                  <l>Here on my Knees to the great Gods I witneſs,</l>
                  <l>How much I love, how much I honour you,</l>
                  <l>My Father and my Friend, even then a Friend,</l>
                  <l>When Heav'n it ſelf had left me, ſever'd me</l>
                  <l>From the lov'd care of an indulgent Parent,</l>
                  <l>Torn from my Arms all that was precious to me,</l>
                  <l>All the dear bleſſings for which ſtill I bow'd</l>
                  <l>In daily thanks before their ſacred Altars.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n then, my Lord, your charitable hand</l>
                  <l>Stood betwixt me and their ſevereſt anger;</l>
                  <l>All this I own, and to the Gods dare ſpeak it.</l>
                  <l>But yet, my honoured Lord —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>But yet <hi>Evanthe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Ungrateful I muſt call her) does reject</l>
                  <l>All the Endearments of an humble Love,</l>
                  <l>Contemns that hand that rais'd her thus to Life:</l>
                  <l>Rais'd her above the reach of Fortune, made her</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106256:6"/>
                  <l>The Idol of Mens Hearts, and Subject of their Tongues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! my Lord, if a ſincere Reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Equal to that with which a pious Child</l>
                  <l>Meets the kind bleſſings of a tender Parent,</l>
                  <l>Are Marks of a Contempt, then let Heav'n witneſs,</l>
                  <l>Let Heav'n and Earth witneſs againſt <hi>Evanthe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A more unworthy Wretch did never taſte</l>
                  <l>A good Man's bounty; this is all I have,</l>
                  <l>How am I able then to pay you more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Not more? Yes more than all the world can give,</l>
                  <l>More than the Gods themſelves, ſhould they vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>To crown <hi>Sorano</hi> with their choiceſt bleſſings.</l>
                  <l>How cunningly you would decline my Suit,</l>
                  <l>And knowing all, affect an Ignorance?</l>
                  <l>Are then theſe ſighs and tears, theſe eyes, that ſpeak</l>
                  <l>A paſſion far too great to be conceal'd;</l>
                  <l>No better known, no better underſtood?</l>
                  <l>Let me then on my Knees —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me on mine</l>
                  <l>Entreat my Lord to pardon his <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſhe confeſſes ſhe can never love:</l>
                  <l>Some ſecret power, too great to be withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Has thrown a fatal Bar between our Hearts,</l>
                  <l>Parted our Souls never to meet in love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Be it ſo then, and by that power I ſwear</l>
                  <l>Never to court your ſcornful beauties more.</l>
                  <l>But know proud Maid there is a Man adores you,</l>
                  <l>Not all your artful Looks, your Womans Pride,</l>
                  <l>Nor the rough hand of fate itſelf, ſhould that</l>
                  <l>Stand betwixt him and his deſires, can ſoften.</l>
                  <l>The King, the haughty King, loves thee <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dotes on thee ev'n to Madneſs, and by Force</l>
                  <l>Will gather all thoſe Virgin Sweets, which I,</l>
                  <l>With my beſt Services, could never merit.</l>
                  <l>Go and prepare you for the royal Sport,</l>
                  <l>Get to your Patches and your Paint, and try</l>
                  <l>By Art to pleaſe this mighty man of power.</l>
                  <l>Learn to look big, and ſtrut it in the Court;</l>
                  <l>Y' have Pride enough, and there it will become you.</l>
                  <l>But when y' have done the buſineſs you was rais'd for,</l>
                  <l>When joys repeated dull the edge of Love,</l>
                  <l>And amorous heat, then to the Stews convey you,</l>
                  <l>There you may thrive, and there I hope to find you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106256:6"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>The King! the King's the Rock that muſt deſtroy me;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtubborn Will, blown by unbounded power,</l>
                  <l>Runs o're all Bars that check him in his Courſe.</l>
                  <l>O my <hi>Valerio</hi> haſten to my ſuccor,</l>
                  <l>Let ſome kind power, the Witneſs of our Vows,</l>
                  <l>Inform thy Soul how much <hi>Evanthe</hi> wants thee.</l>
                  <l>The King! he ſhall be ſerv'd; but how? not this way,</l>
                  <l>Death is a ready Friend on all occaſions,</l>
                  <l>If I can't live a Saint, I'll dye a Martyr.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Q. Mother,</hi> Alphonſo, Piſano, <hi>and</hi> Petruchio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha! Indeed, Madam, you muſt pardon me. I grant you I can ſee every day a muſty Churchman railing at Covetouſneſs in one Room, and his Wife gaming in the next; a merry Poet laughing at a dap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Courtier, and a ſurly Officer grinning at him again; nay, a rich old Alderman inviting the young fellow home to dinner this morning, that lay with his Wife laſt night, and never be mov'd: but to ſee a great Man, nay a Prince dancing to every Fidler —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, who ever did?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you never? bleſs your good fortune then, for it would make your Heart ake to ſee as much as I have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, gentle Son.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, gentle Mother, I know what you would ſay; you would ask me what I want, and alas I want many things; 'twould puzzle a Lawyers Atithmetick to reckon how many things I want. But in the firſt place I want a Wife, for between you and me, Madam, what ſhould ſuch tall overgrown fellows, like myſelf, live any longer without Wives? I know you'll ſay they make Fools of us, why be it ſo, I have been my own Fool long enough, 'tis time now I ſhould be ſome ones elſe; for would one think it, nay freinds you muſt bear me witneſs too, would one think it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Think what, Son?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay nothing, never think on't, my brains are almoſt turn'd with thinking.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <p>For which of all my ſins have I deſerv'd this Curſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>What you weep now, and perhaps 'tis for my Father; and yet I have ſeen ſome women, and they wiſe ones too, do as much for the loſs of a Lap-dog; but, Madam, tell me, did you ever ſee a Lawyer with a Fee in both hands?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Belike I have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then you ſaw the Picture of Juſtice, you'll find his Breviate pinn'd to his back.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, my Son, theſe are disjointed Speeches,</l>
                  <l>The iſſue of a rackt diſtemper'd brain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>That's as much as to ſay I am a Fool, or a Madman; but go tell my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106256:7"/>Brother on't, he'll thank you for the diſcovery; for let me tell you, if 'twas not for Fools, what buſineſs would Knaves have in this world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſee him thus, his Soul thus loſt in darkneſs,</l>
                  <l>Is worſe than death: ye Gods why did his youth</l>
                  <l>Diſcloſe ſuch early hopes of future greatneſs,</l>
                  <l>That blaſted e're age cou'd ſecure 'em to us.</l>
                  <l>Why in the Man do we with ſorrow miſs,</l>
                  <l>What in the Child we did with joy admire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>If the King would make me a Privy Councellor, as I may grow great before I dye, I'de adviſe him to think more, and talk leſs, 'twill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his greatneſs, for now adays there is but this difference betwixt your Wiſe man and your Fool, the Wiſe man laughs at other mens Jeſts, and the Fool always at his own, like a Cat playing with her own Tail, and ſo tickles himſelf with his own fingers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>Obſerve him Gentlemen, and whatſoever</l>
                  <l>A poor unhappy woman's Love can pay</l>
                  <l>You may reſt well aſſur'd of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>We thank your Grace, our beſt care ſhall attend him.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Q. M.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <l>So now I'm free, was ever Love and Pity</l>
                  <l>Unwelcome to a Wretch like me before?</l>
                  <l>Then when ſhe follows, and purſues me moſt,</l>
                  <l>Then when ſhe courts me with her tendereſt love,</l>
                  <l>I ſhun her moſt.</l>
                  <l>A Mother's bleſſing is become my curſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord your cauſeleſs fears create this trouble,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ev'n to her you dare not own your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Whom above all the world you ought to truſt.</l>
                  <l>Diſcloſe your ſelf in time, and make the Queen</l>
                  <l>A happy Partner of the mighty ſecret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <l>No, tho a Queen ſhe is a woman ſtill,</l>
                  <l>A tender Mother, and who knows, my Friend,</l>
                  <l>How far her womans weakneſs may betray her</l>
                  <l>Whilſt my Head wants that Crown, to which ſhe bore me,</l>
                  <l>And I live thus neglected and deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>To her I muſt be mad <hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſtill.</l>
                  <l>But when my honourable friends we have finiſht</l>
                  <l>The glorious task the Gods have laid out for us,</l>
                  <l>Then like her firſt born Son ſhe ſhall behold me,</l>
                  <l>Confeſt a Monarch, and the Lord of power,</l>
                  <l>In whate're you command we ſhall obey.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee this proud imperious Traitor,</l>
                  <l>This beaſt of Prey that ruines all about him,</l>
                  <l>Thrown by the hand of Fate from all his glories,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106256:7"/>
                  <l>Th' untimely fruits of Parricide, and Treaſon.</l>
                  <l>Villain that in the midſt of feign'd pretence,</l>
                  <l>And ſmooth expreſſions of fair Filial duty,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt on his Knees he begg'd a Fathers bleſſing,</l>
                  <l>Dar'd do a deed wou'd damn one but to think on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus miſchief ever wears the cleareſt brow,</l>
                  <l>And like deep waters appears calm and gentle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas difficult to hide his practices;</l>
                  <l>Blood cries aloud, and had it once alarm'd</l>
                  <l>The Peoples Hearts, ſure <hi>Frederick</hi> had wanted</l>
                  <l>That Crown which through ſuch villanies he catch'd at.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>The People? a dull ſenſeleſs lump of Clay,</l>
                  <l>Rude and unform'd, fitted for any impreſſion</l>
                  <l>The cunning Artiſt will impoſe upon it.</l>
                  <l>You know the Story <hi>(To Piſano)</hi> how by ſubtil poiſon</l>
                  <l>He took my Brother's life, attempted mine,</l>
                  <l>But the infuſion met with a reſiſtance</l>
                  <l>Too ſtrong to be o'repower'd: howe're he thought</l>
                  <l>I loſt, what more than Life Men ought to value,</l>
                  <l>My Reaſon;</l>
                  <l>For by your Father's Counſel I put on</l>
                  <l>This outward form of madneſs, to ſecure me</l>
                  <l>From any ſecond blow, the event anſwer'd</l>
                  <l>Our expectations, for being thus deſpis'd</l>
                  <l>I live below his fears.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſure my Lord,</l>
                  <l>The Sword of Juſtice, and <hi>Brandino</hi>'s power,</l>
                  <l>Had been a ſafer, and far nobler refuge.</l>
                  <l>Why did you not inform your Royal Father,</l>
                  <l>Of that dire Plague, that Inſtrument of Hell,</l>
                  <l>Which at laſt fell on his devoted head?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas we did, but we did all in vain.</l>
                  <l>For the curſt Traitor, skill'd i'th' arts of Court,</l>
                  <l>Had ſo prevail'd, ſo won on his belief,</l>
                  <l>That 'twas as eaſie to perſwade my Brother</l>
                  <l>To be what he was not, as make <hi>Brandino</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Believe him what he was; beſides my Father</l>
                  <l>Had nothing but the empty name of <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſhadow left him; for my Brother knew</l>
                  <l>The Power lay lodg'd in bold <hi>Sorano</hi>'s hands,</l>
                  <l>The curſt complotter of his dark deſigns.</l>
                  <l>But no more, fate that by them thought fit to puniſh me,</l>
                  <l>By me at length, I hope, will puniſh them.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106256:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                  <l>My honour'd Lord, where e're You lead we'll follow</l>
                  <l>With an aſſurance that becomes our cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay 'tis a glorious one, and may be worthy</l>
                  <l>The admiration of ſucceeding ages.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſuch a one thoſe brave Old <hi>Roman</hi> Hero's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did they now live, wou'd gladly be embark't in.</l>
                  <l>Who is there living, that e're heard of honour,</l>
                  <l>Or own'd the motions of a generous Spirit,</l>
                  <l>Wou'd tamely lye under th' imperious hand</l>
                  <l>The proud diſdain of an Uſurping Tyrant.</l>
                  <l>Whip him ye Gods! aim all your Thunders at him!</l>
                  <l>Let furies haunt his Dreams, diſtruſt and care</l>
                  <l>Hang on his thoughts, and poiſon all his pleaſures.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petr.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, old <hi>Pedro,</hi> who has plac't his Men</l>
                  <l>In the moſt ſecret corners of the City</l>
                  <l>Will'd me t' inform you that the time calls on us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>That all things now are ripe for Execution;</l>
                  <l>This morning he commands the Guard, by which means</l>
                  <l>The Gates will all be open to receive 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <l>Then e're to Morrow's dawn my Brother ſets,</l>
                  <l>For ever ſets in a dread Cloud of Blood</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Naples</hi> once more ſhall raiſe her drooping head,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rugged Vertues, hard'ned by Afflictions,</l>
                  <l>Shall be the wonder of this lower World,</l>
                  <l>And like old <hi>Rome</hi> give Laws to th' Univerſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My honour'd Lord pardon your Loyal Slave,</l>
                  <l>Who with the foremoſt wiſhes to behold</l>
                  <l>That happy day, and never will know quiet</l>
                  <l>Till we are Maſters of our great deſign;</l>
                  <l>Yet in my humbleſt duty I affirm</l>
                  <l>This day 'twill be impoſſible to effect 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Impoſſible! were he like <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf</l>
                  <l>Clos'd round with Thunder, a guard of Gods,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe every look might awe the Univerſe,</l>
                  <l>Yet then it wou'd not be impoſſible:</l>
                  <l>What can be ſo to minds reſolv'd like ours?</l>
                  <l>But do's he not lye open to deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do not his Friends, that live upon his ſmiles,</l>
                  <l>Rais'd by his favours from the loweſt Earth,</l>
                  <l>Do not ev'n they both fear, and hate the Tyrant?</l>
                  <l>Nay like baſe Slaves wou'd help his ruine forward.</l>
                  <l>Is there a Sword in <hi>Naples</hi> will be Idle,</l>
                  <l>Will not ſtrike home, when the great Gods ſhall call,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106256:8"/>
                  <l>And lead us on to Liberty and Peace?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, all this I grant, and more, but yet—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>But what?</l>
                  <l>Grant me but this, and what more can we ask for</l>
                  <l>The Gods are kind, we wanting to our ſelves;</l>
                  <l>Unſtable unreſolv'd; like heartleſs fools,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill in expectation looſe fruition.</l>
                  <l>I will not truſt my fate to another hazard,</l>
                  <l>To be as great as fortune e're can make me.</l>
                  <l>At length we have got th' unruly beaſt at bay,</l>
                  <l>On ev'ry ſide hem'd in with ſure deſtruction,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall we now forego our certain hopes,</l>
                  <l>Truſt to the bounty of another hour,</l>
                  <l>When this has giv'n us more than we dar'd hope for?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, You us'd to be more moderate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm moderate ſtill, but Vengeance cries aloud.</l>
                  <l>Blood! Treaſon! Parricide! Who is there living</l>
                  <l>Can think of theſe, and keep his uſual Temper?</l>
                  <l>Yet after all the labours of my Soul,</l>
                  <l>Th' Indignities I have with patience born,</l>
                  <l>To make revenge my own, which now ſeems ripe;</l>
                  <l>Waits on our Swords, and ſues for Execution,</l>
                  <l>Thou goeſt about to blunt the edge of Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>And calmly crieſt it is impoſſible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I hate this Tyrant more than you,</l>
                  <l>My Fathers Murder, Brothers Baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>My own diſgrace, have ſworn me to his ruine.</l>
                  <l>Yet when you have heard the reaſons I ſhall urge,</l>
                  <l>Not to rebate or ſlacken your juſt Anger,</l>
                  <l>But to draw back your arm, that with a force</l>
                  <l>Greater and ſurer it may execute,</l>
                  <l>What Heav'n, and your reſentments have determin'd:</l>
                  <l>You'l think your Servant has not judg'd amiſs.</l>
                  <l>'Tis on this day th' Young Soldier brave <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe active Sword deſerves a worthier Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>In warlike form makes his triumphant entry:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Still, ſtill the better; Can we chuſe a day</l>
                  <l>Fitter for our deſign? but that I've known thee</l>
                  <l>Of an experienc'd faith, I ſhou'd miſtruſt thee.</l>
                  <l>Then when his Slaves in their repeated Io's,</l>
                  <l>Their l ud applauſes, raiſe him to the Skies,</l>
                  <l>And place another's Laurels on his brows,</l>
                  <l>Then, then to clip the Wings of this proud Falcon,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106256:9"/>
                  <l>When he ſoars higheſt, and ſink him down to Hell,</l>
                  <l>Will be added to mount us up to Heav'n.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>But Heav'n is ſooner ſcal'd than this perform'd,</l>
                  <l>I mean this way, for ſure my honour'd Lord</l>
                  <l>Has not forgot the cuſtom of his <hi>Naples;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On the return of her Victorious Sons,</l>
                  <l>Who have with foreign Nations fought her battles,</l>
                  <l>None are t' appear in Arms, the day of Triumph;</l>
                  <l>Throughout the City or the Court, but thoſe</l>
                  <l>The General ſhall appoint; to ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That he who fought ſo well abroad, deſerves</l>
                  <l>To rule at home: Shall we then to truſt our fortunes</l>
                  <l>To the ſucceſs of ſuch a raſh attempt?</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe us arm'd, yet how can we prevail</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt ſuch a multitude that will oppoſe us?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter, we are now by much too forward</l>
                  <l>To talk of going back, it will not be,</l>
                  <l>Surely fate interpoſes, and unravels</l>
                  <l>What our beſt care has been ſo long deſigning.</l>
                  <l>Muſt then my Soul be ſtill lock'd up in Priſon</l>
                  <l>Furl'd up in darkneſs and the Womb of Night,</l>
                  <l>Ne're to walk forth again in her own Majeſty?</l>
                  <l>Why have I reaſon and yet dare not uſe it?</l>
                  <l>A Soul for Empire born, yet live a Slave?</l>
                  <l>I'le do't my ſelf: methinks I do behold</l>
                  <l>My Royal Father, and my murder'd Brother,</l>
                  <l>From yon' blue orb inciting me to action.</l>
                  <l>Now their pale Ghoſts, all trembling full of horror,</l>
                  <l>Juſt as they fell, bloated with rankeſt poiſon,</l>
                  <l>In pitious action urge me to revenge:</l>
                  <l>Reſt, reſt in the cold beds of ſilent death,</l>
                  <l>'Till loud revenge ſhall raiſe you, to behold,</l>
                  <l>And wonder at my Juſtice, then in a peal of Thunder</l>
                  <l>Let conſcious Heav'n applaud my miniſtring hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, the day ſucceeding this o'th' Triumph,</l>
                  <l>It being that on which he firſt was Crown'd,</l>
                  <l>The Tyrant dedicates to eaſe, and pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>What hinders but we then compleat his ruine?</l>
                  <l>The Gates lye open to receive all Strangers,</l>
                  <l>That come to grace his Pride, and praiſe his Fortunes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>O my beſt Friend, had I the World to give,</l>
                  <l>It ſhou'd be thine for ſuch another thought:</l>
                  <l>To do it then, will look as if high Heaven</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106256:9"/>
                  <l>Had ſtill preſided o're our pious Counſels,</l>
                  <l>And th' hand of fate had led us to his ruine.</l>
                  <l>Haſt my <hi>Petruchio,</hi> tell old honeſt <hi>Pedro,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Gods are met in Council to determine,</l>
                  <l>And bleſs our high reſolves: the Circle of his Reign</l>
                  <l>Begins to be compleat; the Sun, that gave</l>
                  <l>His Empire birth, muſt light him to his Grave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Frederick <hi>and</hi> Sorano.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>COME to my Arms, my Father, Brother, Friend.</l>
                  <l>To thee thy <hi>Frederick</hi> owes his Life, and Crown,</l>
                  <l>And what he values more than both, his Love,</l>
                  <l>To thee he owes <hi>Evanthe,</hi> his <hi>Evanthe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall ſhe be mine? Shall the kind tender fair one</l>
                  <l>Soften the troubles of ill purchas'd power,</l>
                  <l>And Uſurpation? Shall the Charms of Love</l>
                  <l>Silence the clamours of a guilty Conſcience?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſhall be yours, ſhe is already ſo;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sorano</hi> is the Slave of your deſires,</l>
                  <l>Ready to fling his Soul upon your Service,</l>
                  <l>Nay more his Love; for know I love her too;</l>
                  <l>My active Father, when he firſt inform'd</l>
                  <l>My Mother what a Woman was, ne're knew,</l>
                  <l>Deſires like mine; but yet ſhe ſhall be yours:</l>
                  <l>I that have made you great will make you happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Friend! Father! Brother! are too feeble names</l>
                  <l>T' expreſs my Love; I'le call thee my <hi>Sorano.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How has my Youth been hitherto miſled?</l>
                  <l>Reſtleſs ambition, and the thirſt of Empire,</l>
                  <l>Hung, like an Ague on my active Spirits,</l>
                  <l>Till beauty came to thaw the reſtiff Maſs,</l>
                  <l>New fram'd my Soul, and taught me how to love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Love then, and give a looſe to your deſires,</l>
                  <l>Let your Soul revel in thoſe Charms, that drew</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf from his Coeleſtial Throne,</l>
                  <l>To taſte on Earth Joys he ne're knew in Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes I will Love, but I'le Love like a King;</l>
                  <l>Not quit my Majeſty to be a Slave.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106256:10"/>
                  <l>Whine out an Amorous tale, and dully ask,</l>
                  <l>On my Knees ask, for what I can Command.</l>
                  <l>In Thunder I'le embrace this <hi>Semele.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Firſt try by gentle means to win her Love;</l>
                  <l>If thoſe fall ſhort, then force her to your Arms:</l>
                  <l>I've ſent my Man unto her,</l>
                  <l>Upon ſome private buſineſs to come preſently,</l>
                  <l>Hither ſhe'll come, Your Grace dare ſpeak unto her</l>
                  <l>Large golden promiſes and ſweet Language, Sir</l>
                  <l>You know what they work, ſhe's a compleat Courtier.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, your Servant waits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid him come in, and bring the Lady with him,</l>
                  <l>She's coming in Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Whither doſt thou go?</l>
                  <l>This is the King's ſide, and his private Lodgings,</l>
                  <l>I have no private buſineſs through his Chambers,</l>
                  <l>To ſeek him this way; O my life I find it,</l>
                  <l>Thou art Drunk, or worſe, hired to convey me hither</l>
                  <l>For ſome baſe end. The King here, and <hi>Sorano?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I find I'm trap't; now gentle Love inſpire me,</l>
                  <l>And Honour help in this unequal Combat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay ſhrink not back, the good King will not hurt you,</l>
                  <l>He Honours you, and Loves you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you once did Love, and Honour me,</l>
                  <l>So you have told me oft, and I believ'd it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>I do ſo ſtill, my labours to advance you</l>
                  <l>Proclaim aloud how much I honour you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentle <hi>Evanthe!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>The gentle Queen is well I hear, and now returning home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I talk not of the Queen, I talk of thee, ſweet Flower.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Grace is pleaſant to miſtake a Nettle for a Roſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>No Roſe nor Lilly, nor no glorious Hyacinth,</l>
                  <l>Are of that Whiteneſs, Sweetneſs, Tenderneſs,</l>
                  <l>Softneſs, and ſatisfying bleſſedneſs,</l>
                  <l>As my <hi>Evanthe!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Grace ſpeaks very ſeelingly,</l>
                  <l>I would not be a handſome Wench in your way</l>
                  <l>For a new Gown.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art all handſomneſs,</l>
                  <l>Nature will be aſham'd to frame another,</l>
                  <l>Now thou art made, th'haſt robb'd her of her cunning.</l>
                  <l>But Love <hi>Evanthe!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106256:10"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Good your Grace be patient,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall make the worſt honourable Wench;</l>
                  <l>Shame your Diſcretion, and your Choice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I be Rich do you ſay and Glorious?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt be any thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me be honeſt too, and then I'll thank you.</l>
                  <l>Have you not ſuch a Title to beſtow too?</l>
                  <l>If I prove otherwiſe, I would know but this,</l>
                  <l>Can all the power you have, or all the Riches,</l>
                  <l>But tye Men's Tongues up from diſcourſing of me,</l>
                  <l>Their Eyes from gazing at my glorious folly,</l>
                  <l>Time that ſhall come from wondring at my impudence,</l>
                  <l>And they that read my wanton life, from Curſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay <hi>Evanthe</hi> I'll Marry thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhall the Queen do then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll be Divorc'd from her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you tell why, What has ſhe done againſt you?</l>
                  <l>Has ſhe contriv'd a Treaſon 'gainſt your Perſon,</l>
                  <l>Abus'd your bed, do's diſobedience urge you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis all one, 'tis my will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a moſt wicked one,</l>
                  <l>A moſt abſurd one, and will ſhow a Monſter.</l>
                  <l>I had rather be a Whore, and with leſs ſin,</l>
                  <l>To your preſent Luſt, than Queen to your injuſtice.</l>
                  <l>I'll tell your Grace, ſo Dear I hold the Queen.</l>
                  <l>I'd firſt take me for my Love a <hi>Moor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One of your Gally-Slaves, that cold, and hunger,</l>
                  <l>Decripit miſery had made a mock Man,</l>
                  <l>Than be your Queen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>You are bravely reſolute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I had rather be a Leper, and be ſhunn'd,</l>
                  <l>And dye by pieces, rot into my Grave,</l>
                  <l>And leave no memory behind to know me,</l>
                  <l>Than be a high Whore to eternity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Now my <hi>Sorano,</hi> where's that Reſolution,</l>
                  <l>On which I fondly thought to build my Love?</l>
                  <l>Behold that frown; each look, each word ſhe ſpeaks.</l>
                  <l>At once inflame, and check my ſtrong deſires,</l>
                  <l>I'm like a wretched Slave, half ſtarv'd to Death,</l>
                  <l>That has within his view a goodly Feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet dares not with one Morſel ſave his Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106256:11"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what to think, ſome other gameſter</l>
                  <l>Holds her in play, ſhe durſt not ſlight you elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll find him out, tho' he lye next her heart;</l>
                  <l>Too cruel Maid will nothing win your Love?</l>
                  <l>Brought you thoſe Excellencies to the World</l>
                  <l>To lock 'em in a Caſe, or hang 'em by you?</l>
                  <l>The uſe is all Nature beſtow'd 'em ſor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>But how to uſe 'em right will be the hazard.</l>
                  <l>What's Beauty with a lame decripit Soul?</l>
                  <l>Honour and Riches with a guilty Conſcience?</l>
                  <l>A poor unhappy Orphan this Lord found me,</l>
                  <l>When I had nothing I could call my own;</l>
                  <l>But a variety of miſery,</l>
                  <l>And with a tender hand reliev'd my wants;</l>
                  <l>Preſerr'd me to your Noble Ladies Service,</l>
                  <l>Now my moſt Gracious Queen: where I have learn't</l>
                  <l>And daily fed upon her vertuous precepts;</l>
                  <l>Still growing ſtrong by example of her goodneſs:</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I now dare once but think to wrong her?</l>
                  <l>To violate the chaſt Joys of her Bed?</l>
                  <l>Then farewel Vertue, and all truth in Woman.</l>
                  <l>You may find time out in Eternity,</l>
                  <l>Deceit, and Violence in heavenly Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Life in the Grave, and Death among the bleſſed,</l>
                  <l>Sooner than tempt me to your vain illuſions.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She's gone and flew like ſwifteſt Lightning from me,</l>
                  <l>But left a ſting behind her as ſhe went.</l>
                  <l>Shall I that broke all bars, that cou'd oppoſe me</l>
                  <l>In my purſuit of large imperial power,</l>
                  <l>And in a Purple torrent ſwam to Empire,</l>
                  <l>Bear any oppoſition in my Love:</l>
                  <l>I muſt, <hi>Sorano, Frederick</hi> muſt enjoy her,</l>
                  <l>Tho' ſhe turns fury in my circling Arms,</l>
                  <l>And breaths forth in her Kiſſes ſwift deſtruction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Strive for the preſent to compoſe your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And with fair Signs of Love receive <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tho' you have mark't him down for death ſmile on him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes my <hi>Sorano,</hi> the proud Slave muſt dye;</l>
                  <l>For I remember in my Father's time,</l>
                  <l>Who bred him with his Sons, one Table ſed,</l>
                  <l>One Tutor taught, and one Purſe ſtill ſupply'd us;</l>
                  <l>How he in ſcorn would laugh at my ſlow progreſs,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>th' Exerciſes he grew Maſter of,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106256:11"/>
                  <l>Outrivalling my beſt performances;</l>
                  <l>For which I then did envy, and ſtill hate him.</l>
                  <l>Beſides he grows too popular, and looks</l>
                  <l>With a ſuſpicious Eye upon my greatneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Think him, my Lord, and curſt <hi>Alphonſo</hi> nothing,</l>
                  <l>Whom, tho diſtracted, ſtill the People love,</l>
                  <l>Death waits my pleaſure and ſtands ready for 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Alphonſo <hi>with</hi> Priuli <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>Courtiers more.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſay true, my Lord, <hi>Jaſon</hi> was the man; but what are the times to us? they'll burſt and ſtink when once they are ſwoln with Surfeits; ſtink ſo abominably that all the world ſhall ſmell 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaith my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay 'tis poſſible for poor men to offend, and great forgive, but it muſt not be in the Dog-days. Was you ever in Love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Cour.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>If you have a ſtrong faith then you may be ſaved, but you muſt firſt learn to raviſh twenty or thirty coy Wenches in a morning; tho here they are ſo willing 'tis a complement, for Sir you may be a Bawd, and yet counted an honeſt man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>How do you Brother?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I thank you, ſound in body, and in my right wits; tho ſome hold there's a great difference between a high born Princeſs and a Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers Daughter, but of this you may conſult your Council.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Truſt me! it makes me weep to ſee you thus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>I would bear you Company, but the world goes on ſo merrily I can't find in my heart, ha, ha, ha! Do you ſee that old Lord there? he loſt his wits for want of preferment; but buſh you'll tell the King. Your pardon, my Lord I did not ſee you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord <hi>Alphonſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <p>Wipe your mouth before you ſpeak, my Lord, you'll ſpoil your Speech elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>A warlike Shout within. The Scene draws and diſcovers a Royal Throne on which the King places himſelf, then</hi> Valerio <hi>enters in a Triumphal wanner, being uſhered in with a Song.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Riſe, to my arms, <hi>Valerio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And as a juſt Reward of all thy Labours</l>
                  <l>Accept my Love, and to confirm that Love,</l>
                  <l>Ask what thou wilt, thou ſhalt not ask in vain;</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct thy King, teach him what he muſt do</l>
                  <l>To ſhow how much be loves ſuch early vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Low on my Knees I thank my royal Maſter,</l>
                  <l>And may I be moſt infamouſly wretched,</l>
                  <l>When I forget my Duty to my King.</l>
                  <l>Thus then encourag'd I dare boldly ask,</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106256:12"/>
                  <l>Not as a juſt Reward to crown my labours,</l>
                  <l>For know, Sir, 'tis a gift above all merit;</l>
                  <l>Were I as great as ever <hi>Caeſar</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Pompey</hi> juſt, or <hi>Alexander</hi> valiant;</l>
                  <l>Were all th' exalted Vertues of mankind</l>
                  <l>Blended together to inform one Soul.</l>
                  <l>Were that Soul plac'd in a majeſtick body,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt with an everlaſting youth and beauty,</l>
                  <l>Yet would <hi>Evanthe</hi> far exceed that wonder.</l>
                  <l>And her your Soldier asks for on his knees;</l>
                  <l>Joyn you our hands, my Lord, as Love has joyn'd our hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, my <hi>Sorano!</hi> doſt thou hear the Traitor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Evanthe</hi> ſent <hi>Valerio</hi> to the field,</l>
                  <l>For her I ſuffer'd all the toils of War;</l>
                  <l>Summer Fateigues, and tedious Winter Colds:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Evanthe</hi> led the Soldier forth to fight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Evanthe</hi> gave the word of battle, fought,</l>
                  <l>Conquer'd, and here ſhe comes to crown my Triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Evanthe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>And here ſhe comes to die within theſe Arms,</l>
                  <l>If Fate has not ordain'd ſhe ſhould live there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Live and breed wonders for ſucceeding ages,</l>
                  <l>Be like a never emptied ſpring of joys,</l>
                  <l>Sweeter than life, lovely as ſpotleſs honour;</l>
                  <l>Here let me preſs thee in the arms of Love,</l>
                  <l>Cloſe to my breaſt, to which thou art far dearer</l>
                  <l>Than my own heart that ſallies forth to meet thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Evan.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall I ſay to anſwer all thy kindneſs?</l>
                  <l>I love like thee, but have no time to talk;</l>
                  <l>But fly to view the manſion of my bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Where my bleſt ears ſo often have been fed</l>
                  <l>VVith the ſoft notes of kind indulgent love;</l>
                  <l>My buſy eyes in haſte ſurvey thee round,</l>
                  <l>For fear I ſhould be torn for ever from thee,</l>
                  <l>Before they have renew'd their old acquaintance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>For fear thou ſhould'ſt be torn for ever from me?</l>
                  <l>Life cannot part, and Death ſhall ne're divide us.</l>
                  <l>So well <hi>Valerio</hi> loves thee, O <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That to be thine for one ſhort month I'd give</l>
                  <l>My preſent fortune, hopes of future greatneſs,</l>
                  <l>That ſcene of joys which I ſtill hope to find</l>
                  <l>Laſting as age in my <hi>Evanthe</hi>'s arms.</l>
                  <l>The Sun may move and change the face of Nature;</l>
                  <l>VVe'll know no change, but bleſt in one another,</l>
                  <l>Eternal love and never fading pleaſures</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106256:12"/>
                  <l>Shall fill the courſe of each revolving year.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Guards ſeparate thoſe two.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat means your Highneſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>To interrupt you, Sir, leſt you ſhould ſurfeit,</l>
                  <l>And loſe your ſelf in your imagin'd bliſs.</l>
                  <l>Thou raſh preſumptious Fool! that art ſo prodigal</l>
                  <l>Of love and ſervice, but much more of thy life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I was, Sir, once, when in the face of Death</l>
                  <l>I fought the Cauſe of an ungrateful Maſter.</l>
                  <l>What have I done, Sir, to deſerve your anger?</l>
                  <l>If it be error to deſire to marry,</l>
                  <l>And marry her that Sanctity would dote on,</l>
                  <l>I have done amiſs; if it be a Treaſon</l>
                  <l>To graft my Soul to Vertue, and to grow there,</l>
                  <l>To love the Tree that bears ſuch happineſs;</l>
                  <l>Nay, to deſire to taſte too, I am a Traitor.</l>
                  <l>Had you but Plants enough of this bleſt Tree,</l>
                  <l>Set round about your Court to beautify it,</l>
                  <l>Deaths twice as many to diſmay th' Approachers,</l>
                  <l>The ground would ſcarce yeild Graves to noble Lovers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>aſide to</hi> Al.</stage>
                  <l>This goes as we could wiſh, for now <hi>Valerio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enrag'd at <hi>Frederick</hi>'s unjuſt Refuſal,</l>
                  <l>Will with more eaſe be won to our Deſires,</l>
                  <l>Love and Revenge have made him ours already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Love and Revenge? will thoſe two powerful Miniſters</l>
                  <l>Prevail with him that's deaf to Honours call?</l>
                  <l>Can he, who has with Reſolution born</l>
                  <l>On his Sword's point the Quarrel of a Nation,</l>
                  <l>Yeild up his Life ſo tamely for a Woman?</l>
                  <l>Howe're I'll take him when his manlier Vertues</l>
                  <l>Sit o're his Soul, and bring him home to honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>As for my Life I've hitherto preſerv'd it,</l>
                  <l>And wear it now only to do you ſervice.</l>
                  <l>How I have ſerv'd you, Sir, theſe here can witneſs;</l>
                  <l>I have ſome wounds too may plead ſtrongly for me.</l>
                  <l>But ſince you have deny'd my firſt Requeſt,</l>
                  <l>All other Offers, tho it was your Crown,</l>
                  <l>Bright as it is, I wou'd with ſcorn look down on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well maintain'd. Juſt now I think you wiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>So much you dote upon your own undoing,</l>
                  <l>But for one month t' enjoy her as your VVife,</l>
                  <l>Tho at th'expiring of that time you die for it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I could wiſh many ages, Sir,</l>
                  <l>To grow as old as Time in her Embraces,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106256:13"/>
                  <l>If Heaven wou'd grant it and you-ſmile upon it,</l>
                  <l>But if my Choice were two hours and then periſh,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not pull my Heart back.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You have your wiſh,</l>
                  <l>Immediately I'll ſee you nobly married.</l>
                  <l>Your time take out in all content and pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>But when that time's expir'd you muſt die for it.</l>
                  <l>Kneel not; not all your Prayers can divert me.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, immediate Death ſhould be your doom,</l>
                  <l>But you have done ſome ſervice that pleads for you.</l>
                  <l>Now mark your Sentence, mark it ſcornful Lady,</l>
                  <l>If, when <hi>Valerio</hi>'s dead, within twelve hours,</l>
                  <l>For that's your lateſt time, you find not out</l>
                  <l>Another Husband on the ſame condition,</l>
                  <l>To marry you again, you die your ſelf too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you are merciful, I thank your Grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>If when y' are married you but ſeek t' eſcape</l>
                  <l>Out of the Kingdom, you, or ſhe, or both;</l>
                  <l>Or to infect mens minds with hot Commotions.</l>
                  <l>You die both inſtantly: will you love me now Lady;</l>
                  <l>My Tale will now be heard, but now I ſcorn you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit cum Sur.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Is our fair Love, our honeſt and entire,</l>
                  <l>Come to this hazard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a noble one!</l>
                  <l>Envy could not have ſtudied me a way,</l>
                  <l>Nor Fortune pointed out a Path to Honour</l>
                  <l>Straighter, and nobler, if ſhe had her Eyes.</l>
                  <l>VVhen I have once enjoy'd my ſweet <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And bleſt my Youth with her moſt dear Embraces,</l>
                  <l>I have done my Journey here, my Day is out;</l>
                  <l>All that the world has elſe is foolery;</l>
                  <l>Labour, and loſs of time; what ſhould I live for?</l>
                  <l>Think but Man's life a month, and we are happy.</l>
                  <l>A Paradice, as thou art my <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is only made to wonder at a little,</l>
                  <l>Enough for humane Eyes, and then to wander from</l>
                  <l>Come grudge not my felicity,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll to the Queen his Mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Do any thing that's honeſt,</l>
                  <l>But if you ſue to him in death I hate you.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Ev.</stage>
                  <l>Friends we muſt have a Maſque, I think <hi>Camillo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You are a Poet, pray let me beg this courteſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm glad to ſee you merry, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106256:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Twou'd make you merry had you ſuch a VVife,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch an age t' enjoy her in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>An age, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is't not age to him that is contented?</l>
                  <l>What ſhould I ſeek for more? ſuch Youth and Beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>We confeſs you happy, but on what Price, my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'T were nothing elſe,</l>
                  <l>No Man can ever come to aim at Heaven,</l>
                  <l>But through the knowledge of an Hell. Who would live long?</l>
                  <l>Who would be old? 'tis ſuch a wearineſs,</l>
                  <l>Such a diſeaſe, it hangs like Lead upon us,</l>
                  <l>As it increaſes, ſo vexations,</l>
                  <l>Griefs of the Mind, Pains of the feeble Body,</l>
                  <l>Rheums, Coughs, Catarrhs, we are but our living Coffins.</l>
                  <l>Beſides the fair Soul's old too, it grows covetous,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhows all Honour is departed from us,</l>
                  <l>And we are Earth again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>You make fair uſe, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I would not live to learn to lye, <hi>Cleanthes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For all the world; old men are prone to that too</l>
                  <l>Thou that haſt been a Soldier <hi>Menallo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Adopted thy brave Arm the Heir to Victory</l>
                  <l>Would'ſt thou live ſo long till thy ſtrength forſook thee,</l>
                  <l>Till thou grew'ſt only a long tedious Story,</l>
                  <l>Of what thou haſt been, till thy Sword hung by.</l>
                  <l>And lazy Spiders fill'd the Hilt with Cobwebs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſure I wou'd not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not fit thou ſhou'd'ſt,</l>
                  <l>To dye a Young man is to be an Angel,</l>
                  <l>Our great good parts put Wings upon our Souls.</l>
                  <l>They ſtay ſure, come; I hear the Muſick call us.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit with</hi> Camillo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>We will attend you; Marriage and Hanging go by Deſtiny; 'tis the old Proverb, now they come together, here comes the Ld. <hi>Alphonſo:</hi> how happy had we been if he had reign'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Alphonſo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Tho he is haſty, and his Anger Death,</l>
                  <l>His Will like Torrents not to be reſiſted,</l>
                  <l>Yet Law and Juſtice go along to guide him;</l>
                  <l>And what Law or what Juſtice can he find</l>
                  <l>To juſtifie his Will?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſeems concern'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>One of his melancholy Fits that ne're laſt long.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106256:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet after all Death is unwelcome never,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs it be to tortur'd and ſick Souls.</l>
                  <l>That make their own Hells here on Earth.</l>
                  <l>The poor Slave that lies private, has his Liberty</l>
                  <l>As amply as his Maſter in the Grave;</l>
                  <l>The Earth as light upon him, and the Flowers</l>
                  <l>That grow about him, ſmell as ſweet and flouriſh.</l>
                  <l>But whenſoever it comes crown'd with Honour,</l>
                  <l>When Memory and Vertue are our Mourners,</l>
                  <l>What pleaſures ſhall we then find in the Grave!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>How does your Lordſhip?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well; one, two, three, you can't hurt me for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>What thinks your Lordſhip of this Wedding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <p>They have given him a hot Cuſtard, and mean to burn his mouth with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray, my Lord, what News? theſe Wars have made us Strangers to the Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <p>You may be honeſt, and grow old as I am, and blow your fingers ends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, that's no News.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <p>You may be Knaves then when you pleaſe, ſtark Knaves, and build fair Houſes, but your Heirs ſhall have none of 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are undoubted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth is not worth the hearing: I'll tell you News then, there was a drunken Sailer that got a Mermaid with Child as ſhe went a milking, and now ſhe ſues him in the Bawdy Court for it; the Infant Monſter is brought up in <hi>Fiſh ſtreet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, this is ſomething.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll tell you more, becauſe y' are Soldiers; there was a Fiſh taken, a monſtrous Fiſh, with a Sword by his ſide, a long Sword, a Pike in his Neck, and a Gun in his Noſe, and Letters of Mart in his Mouth, from the Duke of <hi>Florence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>With ſubmiſſion, my Lord, this ſounds ſomething odly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>I do confeſs it; do you think I wou'd tell you truths, that dare not hear'em? You are honeſt things, we Courtiers ſcorn to converſe with.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>He'll grow mad anon and beat us, let us to the Maſque.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Can there be any nature ſo unnoble,</l>
                  <l>Or anger ſo inhumane to purſue this?</l>
                  <l>Yes he, that cou'd not hear the voice of nature</l>
                  <l>That call'd aloud, when by his barbarous hands</l>
                  <l>A Father fell, will have his Ears ſeal'd up</l>
                  <l>In the commiſſion of a meaner Act</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106256:14"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Pedro, Piſano, <hi>and</hi> Petruchio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry'd! yes, when I mean to be hang'd; 'tis the ſurer Contract.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Was not the Monſter ripe for Hell already,</l>
                  <l>He ſhou'd live ſomething longer, to compleat</l>
                  <l>This laſt deſign, and make his damning ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>Why don't we about it then? What do we ſtand preaching for? You, my Lords, may have your quirks and quiddles, your times and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; but I know no more than a Word and a Blow; let us firſt cut his throat, and talk on't afterwards.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay we'll do more than talk, the fatal thread.</l>
                  <l>Which held the Sword of Juſtice o're his head.</l>
                  <l>H' has cut himſelf to make deſtruction ſure.</l>
                  <l>The evening of his Reign draws on apace,</l>
                  <l>But if we don't with timely care prevent him.</l>
                  <l>He'll mark his way with ruine as he falls.</l>
                  <l>And like a fiery Meteor ſet in blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, ſo it be his own 'tis no matter. Why are we not in arms, and the whole City given to know —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſcreetly and privately it muſt be done, 'twill miſs elſe, and prove our ruines; when you all hear the Caſtle Bell take courage and ſtand like Men; mean time be near his perſon to avoid ſuſpicion. I muſt into the preſence, my Mother's fears will work elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit cum</hi> Piſano <hi>and</hi> Petruchio.</stage>
               <stage>Scene draws and diſcovers the Court ſeated for the Maſque, that ended the King ſpeaks.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Come to the Banquet, Sir, when that's ended</l>
                  <l>I'll ſee you in your Bed, and then good night.</l>
                  <l>Be merry; you have a ſweet Bedfellow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I thank your Grace, and ever ſhall be bound unto your Nobleneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray I may deſerve that thanks, ſet forward.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt Omne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106256:15"/>
               <head>ACT III. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>Sorano <hi>Solus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>TO love and be with Scorn and Pride rejected,</l>
                  <l>To ſee another revel in thoſe Joys,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſweet Delights, I now muſt never hope for!</l>
                  <l>Love at the beſt, tho crown'd with ſoft compliance,</l>
                  <l>Is but a ſickly tranſport of the mind,</l>
                  <l>A weakneſs wiſe men ever were aſham'd of;</l>
                  <l>Then when 'tis hopeleſs, what brave Soul can bear it?</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill I love, and loving muſt enjoy.</l>
                  <l>I feel that Fire I once hop'd quite extinct,</l>
                  <l>Dilate it ſelf with a redoubled fury.</l>
                  <l>The King, and this <hi>Valerio</hi> ſtand betwixt</l>
                  <l>Me and my hopes; therefore both ſhall dye.</l>
                  <l>Him I'll make odious for <hi>Valerio</hi>'s death,</l>
                  <l>And mad <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s, what's the conſequence?</l>
                  <l>The people, miſchief-ripe, rais'd by my power,</l>
                  <l>Shall kill the Tyrant, and at once make way</l>
                  <l>For Love and my Ambition. Here comes one</l>
                  <l>Ripe for the combat, and thoſe fancy'd joys</l>
                  <l>Which like a ſhadow ſtill ſhall fly before him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Val.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>They drink abundantly, I'm hot with Wine too,</l>
                  <l>Luſtily warm. I'll ſteal now to my happineſs</l>
                  <l>'Tis midnight, and the ſilent hours invite me.</l>
                  <l>The Dew of Wine and Sleep hang on their Eye-lids;</l>
                  <l>Steep their dull ſenſes in the healths they drink,</l>
                  <l>That I may quickly find my lov'd <hi>Evanthe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>How brisk he is; but I ſhall quickly cool him,</l>
                  <l>Make him wiſh he were dead on's Marriage night,</l>
                  <l>Or bedrid with old age.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not the end of our ambitions,</l>
                  <l>Of all our humane ſtudies,</l>
                  <l>Obtaining of our wiſhes?</l>
                  <l>Certain it is; and there man makes his center.</l>
                  <l>I have my wiſh, what's left me to accuſe now?</l>
                  <l>I'm friends with all the world but thy baſe malice.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Sor.</stage>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106256:15"/>
                  <l>Go, glory in thy miſchiefs, thou proud man,</l>
                  <l>And cry it to the world thou haſt ruin'd vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>You'll ſing me a new Song anon <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And wiſh theſe hot words—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I deſpiſe thee fellow,</l>
                  <l>Thy threats, or flatteries, all I fling behind me,</l>
                  <l>I have obtain'd <hi>Evanthe,</hi> I have marry'd her,</l>
                  <l>And Fate ſhall not with-hold me from enjoying her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very likely,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And that ſhort time I have to bleſs me with her,</l>
                  <l>I'll make an age. I'll reckon each embrace</l>
                  <l>A year of pleaſure, and each night a jubilee;</l>
                  <l>Ev'ry quick kiſs a ſpring, and when I mean</l>
                  <l>To loſe my ſelf in all delightfulneſs,</l>
                  <l>Twenty ſweet Summers I will tye together,</l>
                  <l>I will dye old in love, tho young in pleaſure:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>But that I hate thee deadly, I could pity thee;</l>
                  <l>Thou art the pooreſt miſerable thing</l>
                  <l>This day on earth, I'll tell thee why <hi>Valerio:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All thou eſteemeſt, and build'ſt upon for happineſs,</l>
                  <l>For joy, for pleaſure, for delight, is paſt thee,</l>
                  <l>And like a wanton dream already vaniſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Is my Love falſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>No, ſhe is conſtant to thee;</l>
                  <l>Conſtant to all thy miſery ſhe ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>And curſe thee too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is my ſtrong body weaken'd,</l>
                  <l>Charm'd, or abus'd with ſubtle drink?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Neither; I dare ſpeak thee ſtill as luſty,</l>
                  <l>As when thou lov'dſt her firſt, as ſtrong and hopeful.</l>
                  <l>The month th' haſt given thee is a month of miſery,</l>
                  <l>And where thou think'ſt each hour ſhall yeild a pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Look for a killing pain, for thou ſhalt find it.</l>
                  <l>Before thou dieſt each minute ſhall prepare it,</l>
                  <l>And ring ſo many Knells to ſad afflictions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Undo thy Riddle, I am prepar'd whatever fate ſhall follow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt thou ſee this Ring?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and know it too; 'tis the King's.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <p>Then mark me, by vertue of this Ring this I pronounce thee, 'Tis the King's will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me know it ſuddenly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou doſt offer to touch <hi>Evanthe</hi>'s body,</l>
                  <l>Beyond a kiſs, tho thou art marry'd to her,</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106256:16"/>
                  <l>And lawfully, as thou thinkſt, mayſt enjoy her,</l>
                  <l>That minute ſhe ſhall dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>O Devil —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou diſcover this command unto her,</l>
                  <l>Or to a Friend that ſhall importune thee,</l>
                  <l>Ye both periſh.</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſelf ſame forfeit; how falls your month out now, Sir?</l>
                  <l>Now if you love her you may preſerve her life ſtill,</l>
                  <l>If not you know the worſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This Tyranny could never be invented</l>
                  <l>But in the Schools of Hell, Earth is too innocent,</l>
                  <l>Not to enjoy her when ſhe is my Wife:</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not be ſo monſtrous,</l>
                  <l>As thou proclaimeſt thy ſelf; thou once didſt Love her;</l>
                  <l>And there muſt be a feeling heart within thee,</l>
                  <l>Of her afflictions, wert thou a ſtranger to us,</l>
                  <l>And bred amongſt wild Rocks, thy nature wild too,</l>
                  <l>And unrelenting, as the Rocks that nouriſht thee,</l>
                  <l>Yet thou muſt ſhake to tell me this, they tremble,</l>
                  <l>When the rude Sea threatens divorce amongſt 'em,</l>
                  <l>They that are ſenſeleſs things ſhake at a Tempeſt.</l>
                  <l>Thou art a Man—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Be thou then too. 'twill try thee,</l>
                  <l>And patience now will beſt become thy Nobleneſs.</l>
                  <l>See you obſerve it well, you will find about you</l>
                  <l>Many eyes ſet, that will obſerve your Actions</l>
                  <l>If you tranſgreſs, you know— and ſo I leave you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>The tale of <hi>Tantalus</hi> is now prov'd true,</l>
                  <l>And from me ſhall be regiſtred Authentick.</l>
                  <l>Sure I walk in a miſt, and with that ſilence</l>
                  <l>As if I was the ſhroud I wrapt my ſelf in,</l>
                  <l>And no more of <hi>Valerio</hi> but his ſhadow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Camillo, Cleanthes, Menallo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                  <p>Where have we loſt the Bridegroom? ſure he is gone to bed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>No, here he is thinking no doubt on this nights happineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                  <l>Chear up my Noble Lord, the Minute's come,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall enjoy the abſtract of all ſweetneſs,</l>
                  <l>We did you wrong, you need no Wine to warm you,</l>
                  <l>Deſire ſhoots through your Eyes like ſudden Wildfires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>In troth my Lords, the Wine has made me dull,</l>
                  <l>I am I know not what.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>O there's a Lady coming will inform you.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106256:16"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Frederick <hi>and</hi> Sorano.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Tho there are left ſmall hopes for his recovery,</l>
                  <l>That hope ſtill lives, and Mens eyes live upon it.</l>
                  <l>And in their eyes their wiſhes for <hi>Alphonſo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were he but cold once in the ſilent Grave,</l>
                  <l>As 'tis the fitteſt place for Melancholy,</l>
                  <l>My Court ſhould be another Paradice,</l>
                  <l>And flow with all delights.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to your pleaſures let me alone with this</l>
                  <l>But mark the Man you'll ſcarce know 'tis <hi>Valerio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Good pleaſure to you,</l>
                  <l>Good night, and long too, as you find your appetite</l>
                  <l>You may fall to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I do beſeech your Grace</l>
                  <l>For which of all my faithful ſervices</l>
                  <l>Have I deſerv'd this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not bound to anſwer you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor I bound to obey in unj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt actions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Do as you pleaſe, you know the Penalty;</l>
                  <l>And as I have a Soul it ſhall be executed.</l>
                  <l>Nay look not pale I am not us'd to fear, Sir.</l>
                  <l>If you reſpect your Lady good night to you.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex. cum</hi> Sor.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But for reſpect to her, and to my duty,</l>
                  <l>Which anger has no power to rob me of,</l>
                  <l>The good night ſhou'd be thine, good night for ever.</l>
                  <l>How my heart trembles</l>
                  <l>And beats my breaſt, as it wou'd break it's way out.</l>
                  <l>Good night my noble friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, we muſt ſee you towards your bed, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, it needs not, 'tis late, and I ſhall trouble you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, till the Bride come, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I beſeech you leave me.</l>
                  <l>You will make me baſhful, I am ſo fooliſh,</l>
                  <l>Beſides I have ſome few devotions, Lords,</l>
                  <l>And he that can pray with ſuch a book in his arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll leave you then, and a ſweet night wait on you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                  <p>And a ſweet iſſue of this ſweet night crown you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                  <p>All nights and days be ſuch till you grow old, Sir.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank ye: 'tis a curſe ſufficient for me,</l>
                  <l>A labour'd one too, tho you mean a bleſſing.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I do? I'm like a wretched Debtor,</l>
                  <l>That has a ſumm to tender on the forfeit</l>
                  <l>Of all he's worth, yet dare not offer it.</l>
                  <l>Other men ſee the Sun, but I muſt wink at it,</l>
                  <l>And tho I know 'tis perfect day deny it.</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106256:17"/>
                  <l>I muſt enjoy her, yet when I conſider</l>
                  <l>The Tyrant's will, and his power taught to murder,</l>
                  <l>My tender care controuls my blood within me,</l>
                  <l>And like a cold fit of a peeviſh Ague</l>
                  <l>Creeps to my Soul, and flings an Ice upon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Q. Mother,</hi> Evanthe, <hi>and Lady.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Evanthe,</hi> make ye unready, your Lord ſtays for you,</l>
                  <l>And prithee be merry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Grace deſires what is too free in me,</l>
                  <l>I am ſo taken up in all my thoughts,</l>
                  <l>So poſſeſt, Madam, with the lawful ſweets,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall this night partake of with my Lord,</l>
                  <l>So far tranſported, pardon my immodeſty,</l>
                  <l>That tho they muſt be ſhort, and ſnatcht away too,</l>
                  <l>E're they grow ripe, yet I ſhall far prefer 'em</l>
                  <l>Before a tedious pleaſure with Repentance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>O how my heart akes!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M</speaker>
                  <l>I thank thee heartily</l>
                  <l>For learning how to uſe thy few hours handſomly,</l>
                  <l>They will be years I hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Good night, dear Madam.</l>
                  <l>Ladies, no farther ſervice, I am well:</l>
                  <l>I do beſeech your Grace to give us this leave;</l>
                  <l>My Lord and I to one another freely,</l>
                  <l>And privately may do all other Ceremonies,</l>
                  <l>Woman and Page we'll be to one another,</l>
                  <l>And trouble you no farther.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then good night, good night, my beſt <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou worthy Maid, and as that name ſhall vaniſh,</l>
                  <l>A worthy Wife, a long and happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſhall be my care.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. M.</speaker>
                  <l>Be chearful Lord, and take your Lady to ye,</l>
                  <l>And that power that ſhall part you be unhappy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet reſt unto ye, to you all ſweet Ladies.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Q. M.</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you to bed my Lord, come let me help you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>To bed, <hi>Evanthe;</hi> art thou ſleepy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>No; but I ſhall be worſe if you look ſad upon me;</l>
                  <l>Pray let's to bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not well, my Love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll make you well; there's no ſuch Phyſick for you,</l>
                  <l>As your warm Miſtreſs's arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Art thou ſo cunning?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſpeak not by experience, pray miſtake not,</l>
                  <l>But if you love me—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106256:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I do love ſo dearly,</l>
                  <l>So much above the baſe bent of deſire,</l>
                  <l>I know not how to anſwer thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>To bed then,</l>
                  <l>There I ſhall better credit you: Fie, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Will you put a Maid to't, to teach you what to do,</l>
                  <l>An innocent Maid, are you ſo cold a Lover?</l>
                  <l>This is no ſtolen Love, or a ſin we covet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>May I not love thy Mind?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>And I yours too,</l>
                  <l>'Tis a moſt noble one adorn'd with Vertue.</l>
                  <l>But if we love not one another really,</l>
                  <l>And put our Bodies and our Minds together,</l>
                  <l>And ſo make up the concord of affection,</l>
                  <l>Our love will prove but a blind ſuperſtition.</l>
                  <l>This is no School to argue in, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Nor have we time to talk away allow'd us,</l>
                  <l>Come kiſs me and to bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>That I dare do, and kiſs again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Spare not they are your own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My Veins are all on Fire, and burn like <hi>Aetna,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Youth, and deſire beat Larums to my Blood,</l>
                  <l>And add freſh fuel to my warm affections.</l>
                  <l>Haſt thee, <hi>Evanthe,</hi> to the Genial bed,</l>
                  <l>The happy Scene of our approaching Bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And Joys bleſt Lovers never knew before;</l>
                  <l>Yes we will love, not all the powers on Earth,</l>
                  <l>Or Hell it ſelf ſhall ever hope to part us.</l>
                  <l>Each Minute as it ſwiftly glides along,</l>
                  <l>Shall bear the pleaſures of whole Ages with it,</l>
                  <l>And witneſs to the reſt our ſpotleſs Love.</l>
                  <l>Great Love himſelf, with his officious Wings,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n in the midſt of all our furious tranſports</l>
                  <l>Shall gently raiſe and ſtrengthen our deſires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Come lets diſpatch then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>It will not be, for when I weigh her danger,</l>
                  <l>The thoughts of that lock up all powers of youth.</l>
                  <l>O what a bleſſedneſs 'twere to be old now,</l>
                  <l>Or half on Crutches to meet holy Hymen!</l>
                  <l>That that ſpeaks other men moſt freely happy,</l>
                  <l>And makes all eyes hang on their expectations,</l>
                  <l>Youth, and Ability muſt prove my bane.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, fie my Lord, if any one ſhou'd come,</l>
                  <l>And find us at this diſtance, what wou'd they think?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106256:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>No to enjoy thee is to be luxurious</l>
                  <l>O how I burn! to pluck thee from the Stalk,</l>
                  <l>Where now thou grow'ſt a ſweet and heavenly Flower,</l>
                  <l>And bear'ſt the prime, and honour of the Garden,</l>
                  <l>Is but to violate thy Spring, and ſpoil thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>To let me blow, and fall alone wou'd anger ye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's ſit together thus, and as we ſit</l>
                  <l>Feed on the ſweets of one anothers Souls,</l>
                  <l>Where no allay of actual dull deſires,</l>
                  <l>Of humane fire, that burns out as it kindles,</l>
                  <l>Can ever mix, let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s fix on that, <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That's everlaſting, the other caſual,</l>
                  <l>Eternity breeds one, the other Fortune,</l>
                  <l>Blind as her ſelf, and full of all Afflictions,</l>
                  <l>Shall we love vertuouſly?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>I ever lov'd ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And only think our love: the rareſt pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>And that we moſt deſire, let it be humane,</l>
                  <l>If once enjoy'd, grows ſtale, and cloys our appetite.</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not leſſen in my love for any thing,</l>
                  <l>Nor find thee but the ſame in my ſhort Journey,</l>
                  <l>For my loves ſafety.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I ſee I'm old, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Old, and ill-favour'd too, poor, and deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>And am not worthy your noble fellowſhip,</l>
                  <l>Your fellowſhip in Love, you wou'd not elſe</l>
                  <l>Thus cunningly ſeek to betray a Maid,</l>
                  <l>Strive to abuſe the pious love ſhe brings you;</l>
                  <l>Farwel, my Lord, ſince you have another Miſtreſs —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, my <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Heav'n bear em witneſs, thou art all I love,</l>
                  <l>All I deſire, and now have pity on me,</l>
                  <l>As I ſhall want it much. Forgive me Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Youth, and affection ſtop your ears unto me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Aſide:</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Why do you Weep, if I have ſpoke too harſhly,</l>
                  <l>And unbeſeeming my belov'd Lord,</l>
                  <l>My care and duty pardon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O hear me,</l>
                  <l>Hear me, <hi>Evanthe;</hi> I am all on torture,</l>
                  <l>And this lye tears my Conſcience as I vent it.</l>
                  <l>I am no Man.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>How Sir!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>No Man for pleaſure, no Womans Man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Goodneſs forbid, my Lord, fure you abuſe your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106256:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true, <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>He weeps bitterly.</l>
                  <l>'Tis my hard fortune, bleſs all young Maids from it,</l>
                  <l>Is there on help my Lord in art will comfort ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope there is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis hard to die for nothing;</l>
                  <l>Now you ſhall know 'tis not the pleaſure, Sir,</l>
                  <l>That Women aim at, I affect you for,</l>
                  <l>'Tis for your Worth, nay I ſtill honour you,</l>
                  <l>And with all duty to my Husband follow you.</l>
                  <l>Will you to bed now, you are aſham'd it ſeems;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pigmalion</hi> pray'd, and his cold ſtone took life,</l>
                  <l>You do not know with what zeal I ſhall ask, Sir,</l>
                  <l>And what rare miracle that may work on you,</l>
                  <l>Still bluſh? preſcribe your Law.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I prithee pardon me,</l>
                  <l>To bed, and I'll ſit by thee, and mourn with thee.</l>
                  <l>I pray to Heaven when I am gone, <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As my poor date is but a Span of Time now,</l>
                  <l>To recompence thy noble patience,</l>
                  <l>Thy Love, and Vertue, with a fruitful Husband,</l>
                  <l>Honeſt, and Honourable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Come you have made me weep now.</l>
                  <l>All fond deſires die, here, and welcome Chaſtity:</l>
                  <l>As for this Tyrant, we'll ſo torture him,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a pious ſcorn, that we will ſhake him;</l>
                  <l>And when <hi>Valerio,</hi> and <hi>Evanthe</hi> ſleep</l>
                  <l>In one rich Earth, hung round about with bleſſings,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall grow mad with ſhame, repent too late,</l>
                  <l>And ſink I th' ruines of our happier fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <trailer>The end of the third Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106256:19"/>
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Frederick.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>MEthinks the Sun this morning mounts the Sky,</l>
                  <l>With a pale face, and Death plays in his Beams.</l>
                  <l>Why, be it ſo, they dart it on <hi>Alphonſo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But add new life to my continu'd pleaſures.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sorano</hi>'s always witty in his miſchief,</l>
                  <l>To Poyſon him, and by my Mothers hand,</l>
                  <l>Will be a double ſtroke, and ſweep away</l>
                  <l>The only bars, that check my ſweet delights.</l>
                  <l>Cou'd I but gain this Maid too I were happy.</l>
                  <l>Come hither Time, how does your noble Miſtreſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caſſandra.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>As a Gentlewoman may do in her Caſe, that's newly marri'd,</l>
                  <l>Sickly, and fond on't, and pleaſe your Majeſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>She's breeding then, and eats good Broths and Jellies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm ſure ſhe ſighs, Sir, and weeps, good Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Alaſs good Lady for it!</l>
                  <l>She ſhou'd have one cou'd comfort her, <hi>Caſſandra,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cou'd turn thoſe Tears to Joys, a luſty comforter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>A comfortable man does well at all hours,</l>
                  <l>For he brings comfortable things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Come hither, and hold your Fan between, you have eaten Onions;</l>
                  <l>Her breath ſtinks like a Fox, her teeth are Contagious,</l>
                  <l>Theſe old Women are all Elder Pipes, do you mark me. He gives her a Purſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>But does your Grace think I am fit, that am both old and vertuous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore the fitter, the older ſtill the better,</l>
                  <l>I know thou art as holy as an old Cope.</l>
                  <l>Yet upon neceſſary uſe—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Her feeling ſenſe is fierce ſtill; ſpeak unto her,</l>
                  <l>You are familiar; ſpeak I ſay unto her,</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106256:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Alaſs ſhe's honeſt Sir, ſhe's very honeſt,</l>
                  <l>And wou'd you have my gravity?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I, I, your gravity will become the Cauſe the better:</l>
                  <l>I'll look thee out a Knight ſhall make thee a Lady too,</l>
                  <l>A luſty Knight, and one that ſhall be rul'd by thee.</l>
                  <l>Come, come, no ducking out of nicety,</l>
                  <l>But do it home, we'll all be friends too tell her,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a Joy —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>That's it that ſtirs me up, Sir.</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not for the world attempt her Chaſtity,</l>
                  <l>But that they may live lovingly together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>For that I urge it too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>A little evil may well be ſuffer'd for a general good,</l>
                  <l>I'll take my leave of your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Go and be fortunate, I know he wants no additions to his tortures;</l>
                  <l>He has enough for humane blood to carry,</l>
                  <l>So many, that I wonder his hot Youth,</l>
                  <l>And high bred Spirit breaks not into Fury.</l>
                  <l>Yet I muſt torture him a little further,</l>
                  <l>My anger is too poor elſe. Here they come.</l>
                  <l>Th' old Woman ſeems an earneſt advocate</l>
                  <l>They are ſtrange things, but I muſt not be ſeen.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Evanthe</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>You think it fit then, Mortified <hi>Caſſandra</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That I ſhou'd be a Whore?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>If every woman, that upon neceſſity</l>
                  <l>Did a good turn, were term'd a Whore,</l>
                  <l>Who wou'd be honeſt.</l>
                  <l>Your Lords life, and your own, are now in hazard.</l>
                  <l>Two precious lives may be redeem'd with nothing:</l>
                  <l>That we call luſt, that Maidens looſe their ſame for,</l>
                  <l>But a Compell'd neceſſity of honour,</l>
                  <l>Fair as the day, and clear as innocence,</l>
                  <l>Upon my life and conſcience, a direct way—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>To be a Devil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a kind of rape too,</l>
                  <l>That keeps you clear; for where the will's compell'd</l>
                  <l>Tho' you yield up your body, you are ſafe ſtill</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art grown a learned Bawd, I ever look't</l>
                  <l>Thy great ſufficiency wou'd break out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>You may</l>
                  <l>You that are young and fair from us old Creatures.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106256:20"/>
                  <l>But you muſt know my years e're you be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And my experience too. Say the King lov'd ye</l>
                  <l>Do you think Princes favours are ſuch trifles,</l>
                  <l>To fling away when you pleaſe? there are young Ladies,</l>
                  <l>Both fair, and honourable, that wou'd leap to reach 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>They are the wiſer for it; but canſt thou tell me</l>
                  <l>Tho' he be a King whether he be ſound or no?</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not give my youth up to infection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>As ſound as honour ought to be I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>But when I have lain with him, what am I then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>What are you? why the ſame you are now, a woman,</l>
                  <l>A vertuous woman, and a noble woman,</l>
                  <l>Touching at what is noble you become ſo.</l>
                  <l>Had <hi>Lucreece</hi> e're been thought of, but for <hi>Tarquin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She was before a Simple unknown woman,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe was raviſh't, ſhe was a reverent St.</l>
                  <l>And do you think ſhe yielded not a little,</l>
                  <l>And had a kind of will to be re-raviſh't:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſuppoſe the King ſhou d ſo delight me,</l>
                  <l>I ſhou'd forget my Lord, and no more look on him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>That's the main hazard, for I tell you truly,</l>
                  <l>I've heard report ſpeak him an infinite pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace, thou old Bawd, thou ſtudyed old corruptneſs.</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou ſeek to make me dote on wickedneſs,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe 'tis ten times worſe than thou deliver'ſt it?</l>
                  <l>To be a Whore, O thou Impudence!</l>
                  <l>Have I reliev'd thy Age to my own ruin?</l>
                  <l>And worn thee in my boſom to betray me?</l>
                  <l>Can years, and Impotence win nothing on thee</l>
                  <l>That's good and honeſt, but thou muſt go on ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And where thy Blood wants heat to ſin thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Force thy decrepid will to make me wicked?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I did but tell ye —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>What the damndeſt Woman,</l>
                  <l>The cunningſt, and moſt skillfull Bawd, comes ſhort of.</l>
                  <l>If thou hadſt liv'd ten ages to be damn'd in,</l>
                  <l>And exercis'd this art the Devil taught thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou couldſt not have expreſt it more exactly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not bid you ſin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wood'ſt me to it.</l>
                  <l>Thou that art fit for Prayer, and the Grave,</l>
                  <l>Thy Body Earth already, and Corruption,</l>
                  <l>Thou taught<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt the way; go follow your fine Function,</l>
                  <l>There are houſes of Delight, that want good Matrons,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106256:20"/>
                  <l>Such grave Inſtructors, get thee thither, Monſter,</l>
                  <l>And read varitey of Sins to Wantons,</l>
                  <l>And when they roar with pains then learn to pity 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>This we have for our good will;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>When thou want'ſt bread, and common pity towards thee;</l>
                  <l>When thou art ſtarving in a Ditch, think on me,</l>
                  <l>Then die and let the wandring Bawds lament thee.</l>
                  <l>Begone I charge thee leave me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Caſſandra.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Frederick.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She's angry, and the other gone, my ſuits cold.</l>
                  <l>I'll make your heart ake, ſtubborn Maid, for this.</l>
                  <l>Turn not ſo angry from me, I will ſpeak to you;</l>
                  <l>Are you grown proud with your delight, good Lady,</l>
                  <l>So pamper'd with your ſport, you ſcorn to know me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſcorn you not, I wiſh you ſcorn'd not me, Sir;</l>
                  <l>And forc't me to be weary of my duty.</l>
                  <l>I know your Grace, wou'd I had never ſeen you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe I love, becauſe I dote upon you,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I am a man, that ſeek to pleaſe you</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I've one already, Sir, that can content me,</l>
                  <l>As much, as noble, and as worthy of me</l>
                  <l>As all the world can yield.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>That's but your modeſty.</l>
                  <l>You have no man, nay never look upon me,</l>
                  <l>I know it Lady, no man to content ye;</l>
                  <l>No man that can, or at the leaſt that dares,</l>
                  <l>Which is a poorer man, and nearer nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Be nobler Sir inform'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll, tell you, Madam,</l>
                  <l>The poor condition of this poorer Fellow,</l>
                  <l>And make you bluſh for ſhame at your own error.</l>
                  <l>He has not render'd yet a Husbands duty</l>
                  <l>To your warm longing Bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhou'd he know that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure he did not, for I charg'd him no,</l>
                  <l>Upon his life I charg'd him, but to try him.</l>
                  <l>Cou'd any brave or noble ſpirit ſtop here?</l>
                  <l>Was life to be prefern'd before affection,</l>
                  <l>Lawful and long d for too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you command him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I did in policy, to try his ſpirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>And cou'd he be ſo dead cold to obſerve it?</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:106256:21"/>
                  <l>Brought I no Love nor Beauty along with me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhou d have lov'd him if he had ventur'd for it,</l>
                  <l>Nay doted on his bravery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Only charg'd, and with that ſpell ſit down: dare men fight bravely</l>
                  <l>For poor ſlight things, for drink or oſtentation</l>
                  <l>And there indanger both their lives and fortunes?</l>
                  <l>And for their lawful loves fly off with fear?</l>
                  <l>I wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d have died a thouſand deaths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>So wou d any,</l>
                  <l>Any that had the ſpirit of a Man.</l>
                  <l>I wou'd have been kill'd, in your Arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh I had been,</l>
                  <l>And buryed in my arms, that had been noble;</l>
                  <l>And what a Monument wou'd I have made him!</l>
                  <l>Upon my breaſt he ſhould have ſlept in peace,</l>
                  <l>Honour, and everlaſting love his Mourners;</l>
                  <l>And I ſtill weeping 'till old time had turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d me,</l>
                  <l>And pitying powers above, into pure Chryſtal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hadſt thou lov'd me, and had my way been ſtuck</l>
                  <l>With deaths, as thick as froſty nights with Stars,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd have ventur'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Sir afflict me not too faſt, I feel</l>
                  <l>I am a Woman, and a wrong'd one too,</l>
                  <l>And I am ſenſible of my abuſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>All reaſon, and all Laws allow it ye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>You may ſpeak now, and happily prevail too.</l>
                  <l>And I beſeech your Grace be angry with me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>If I ſhou'd give him life he wou'd betray thee,</l>
                  <l>That fool that fears to die for ſuch a Beauty,</l>
                  <l>Wou'd for the ſame fear ſell thee unto miſery.</l>
                  <l>I do not ſay he ſet your Woman on you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Follow'd thus far, nay then I ſmell the malice,</l>
                  <l>It taſts too hot of practis'd wickedneſs.</l>
                  <l>Shall my Anger make me Whore, and not my pleaſure?</l>
                  <l>My ſudden inconſiderate rage abuſe me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor he wou'd have been himſelf Sollicitor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor do not dare, 'twill be an imprudence,</l>
                  <l>And not an honour for a Prince to lye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>How lye?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Shamefully, and I cou'd wiſh my ſelf a man but one day,</l>
                  <l>To tell you openly you lye too baſely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed wild ſool.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Take heed thou tame Devil,</l>
                  <l>Thou all <hi>Pandora</hi>'s box in a Kings figure;</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106256:21"/>
                  <l>Thou haſt almoſt whor'd my weak belief already,</l>
                  <l>And like an Engineer blown up my Honour,</l>
                  <l>But I ſhall countermine, and catch your miſchief.</l>
                  <l>Victorious <hi>Thomyris,</hi> ne'er won more honour,</l>
                  <l>In cutting off the Royal Head of <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than I ſhall do in conquering thee, farewell.</l>
                  <l>And if thou canſt be wiſe learn to be good too,</l>
                  <l>'Twill give thee nobler light than both thy eyes do.</l>
                  <l>My poor Lord and my ſelf are bound to ſuffer,</l>
                  <l>And when I ſee him faint under your ſentence,</l>
                  <l>I'll tell you more, it may be than I'll yield to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yielding or not I've ſworn ſhe ſhall be mine,</l>
                  <l>Tho I ſhou'd wade through Seas of blood to meet her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Val.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He's here and by himſelf, what hinders me,</l>
                  <l>But that I now make ſure a noble vengeance?</l>
                  <l>The People do expect, the Soldiers wiſh it,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Naples</hi> hang on me their expectations.</l>
                  <l>As if it was a debt, I ow'd my Country.</l>
                  <l>But ſtill he is my Soveraign, and that thought</l>
                  <l>Pulls back my Sword, and turns the edge againſt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Now my young marry'd Lord how do you feel your ſelf?</l>
                  <l>You have the happineſs you ever aim'd at,</l>
                  <l>The joy and pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>You tumble in delights, with your ſweet Lady,</l>
                  <l>And draw the Minutes out in dear imbraces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Wou'd you had try'd it, Sir, that you might know</l>
                  <l>The vertue but to ſuffer.</l>
                  <l>Your anger tho' it be unjuſt, and inſolent,</l>
                  <l>Sits handſomer upon you than your ſcorn.</l>
                  <l>To do a willfull ill, and glory in it,</l>
                  <l>Is to do it double, and doubly to be damn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You clearly ſee now, brave <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What 'tis to be a rival to a Prince,</l>
                  <l>To interpoſe agianſt a raging Lyon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>You are grown a Tyrant</l>
                  <l>Upon ſo ſuffering, and ſo ſtill a Subject,</l>
                  <l>That if your youth were honeſt, it wou'd bluſh at.</l>
                  <l>But y'are a ſhame to nature, as to vertue;</l>
                  <l>Pull not my rage upon ye, 'tis ſo Juſt</l>
                  <l>It will give way to no reſpect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I know y'ave ſuffer'd, infinitely ſuffer'd,</l>
                  <l>And with a kind of pity I behold ye;</l>
                  <l>And if you dare be worthy of my mercy,</l>
                  <l>I can yet heal you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I fall thus low, Sir.</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106256:22"/>
                  <l>And my poor heart under your feet I lay,</l>
                  <l>And all the ſervice of my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I o this then</l>
                  <l>Part with her for a while.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>You have parted us,</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I do with that I cannot uſe, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well conſider'd; let me have the Lady,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt ſee how nobly I'll befriend thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Will ſhe come do you think?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She muſt be wrought, I know ſhe is too modeſt,</l>
                  <l>And that with Art.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But who ſhall work her, Sir?</l>
                  <l>For on my conſcience ſhe is very honeſt,</l>
                  <l>And will be hard to cut as a rough Diamond.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, you muſt work her, any thing from your Tongue,</l>
                  <l>Set off with Golden, and perſwaſive language,</l>
                  <l>Urging your dangers too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But all this while</l>
                  <l>Have you the Conſcience, Sir, to leave me nothing;</l>
                  <l>Nothing to play withall?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>There are ten thouſand, take where thou wilt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>May I be bold with your Queen,</l>
                  <l>She's uſeleſs to your Grace, as it appears, Sir,</l>
                  <l>And but a Loyal Wife that may be loſt too,</l>
                  <l>I have a mind to her, and then 'tis equal,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſo, Sir; thou moſt glorious impudence,</l>
                  <l>Have I not wrongs enow to ſuffer under,</l>
                  <l>But thou muſt pick me out to make a Monſter,</l>
                  <l>A hated wonder to the World! do you ſtart</l>
                  <l>At my intrenching on your private liberty,</l>
                  <l>And wou'd you force a high way through my honour,</l>
                  <l>And make me pave it too? but that thy Queen</l>
                  <l>Is of that excellent honeſty,</l>
                  <l>And guarded with Divinity about her,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd ſo right my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Why take her to you,</l>
                  <l>I am not vext at this; thou ſhalt enjoy her,</l>
                  <l>I'll be thy Friend if that will win thy curteſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not be your Bawd tho' for your Kingdom.</l>
                  <l>Was I brought up and nouriſh'd in the Court</l>
                  <l>With thy moſt Royal Brothers and thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And ſuck't the ſweetneſs of all humane Arts,</l>
                  <l>Learn'd arms and honour to become a villain?</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106256:22"/>
                  <l>Was this the expectation of my youth,</l>
                  <l>My growth and glory. Do you ſpeak this truly,</l>
                  <l>Or do you try me, Sir; for I believe not,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt I wou'd not, and methinks 'tis impoſſible</l>
                  <l>There ſhou'd be ſuch a Devil in a King's ſhape.</l>
                  <l>Such a malignant Fiend!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You'll find me worſe if you perſiſt thus raſhly,</l>
                  <l>The next time you hear from me it muſt be</l>
                  <l>In rougher terms, and ſo I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Am I a Man and feel loves fire within me,</l>
                  <l>Youth and deſire engaging me to taſte,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſweet delights the law has given me?</l>
                  <l>Have I within my reach that precious treaſure,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe which I have ſacrific'd my life,</l>
                  <l>Withall my youthful hopes, and ſhall I not</l>
                  <l>Becauſe a Tyrants power interpoſes</l>
                  <l>Dare once to touch that dear bought happineſs.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Evanthe.</stage>
                  <l>Come my <hi>Evanthe,</hi> fly into my Arms,</l>
                  <l>Let thy warm ſighs diſſolve that lump of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>That heavy load that hangs upon my ſoul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Not all my ſighs, nor the ſincereſt love,</l>
                  <l>That e're was paid by an unhappy Maid,</l>
                  <l>Can purge thy ſoul of its ingratitude.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Canſt thou look up to the peoples love,</l>
                  <l>That call thee worthy and not bluſh, <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can'ſt thou behold me, whom thou haſt betray'd,</l>
                  <l>Yet know no ſhame?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What means my beſt <hi>Evanthe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſave thy life, and for ſo ſhort a time;</l>
                  <l>It do's betray ſo baſe a Cowardice,</l>
                  <l>That makes ev'n me a Woman bluſh to think on't.</l>
                  <l>Had twenty thouſand deaths attended me</l>
                  <l>I wou'd have met 'em all, and di'd upon the pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I'am all amazement!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>To let a lye work like a ſpell upon ye,</l>
                  <l>A lye to ſave your life; the King himſelf,</l>
                  <l>Tho he be wicked, and our Enemy,</l>
                  <l>But juſter than thou art, in pity of me</l>
                  <l>Told me this truth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What did he tell you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>That but to gain thy life for a few days,</l>
                  <l>Thy lov'd poor life, thou gaveſt up all my duties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſwear 'tis falſe, my life and death are equal.</l>
                  <l>But Kings are men, and live and die as men do,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106256:23"/>
                  <l>Have the affections men have, and their falshoods.</l>
                  <l>Indeed they have more power to make 'em good.</l>
                  <l>It was to ſave thy life, thy innocent life,</l>
                  <l>That I forbore thy bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>And was not I as worthy to die nobly,</l>
                  <l>To make a ſtory for the times that follow,</l>
                  <l>As he that married me? do you think I choſe you</l>
                  <l>Only for pleaſure, or content in Love,</l>
                  <l>To lull you in my arms and kiſs you hourly?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not think ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>I might have been a Queen, Sir,</l>
                  <l>If that had caught me, and have known all delicates.</l>
                  <l>There's few that wou'd have ſhun'd ſo fair an offer.</l>
                  <l>O thou unfaithful fearful man, thou haſt kill'd me;</l>
                  <l>In ſaving me this way thou haſt deſtroy'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I honour you; by all the rites of marriage</l>
                  <l>And pleaſures of chaſt love, I wonder at you.</l>
                  <l>You appear the viſion of a heaven unto me,</l>
                  <l>Stuck all with ſtars of honour ſhining clearly;</l>
                  <l>Why don't you chide me, you have ſo brave an anger,</l>
                  <l>And thus deliver'd flows ſo nobly from you,</l>
                  <l>That I cou'd ſuffer like a child to hear you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>My Anger's gone, good my Lord pardon me,</l>
                  <l>And if I have offended be more angry.</l>
                  <l>It was a womans flaſh, a ſudden valour</l>
                  <l>That cou'd not lie conceal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</l>
                  <l>You have with a cunning patience chek't my folly.</l>
                  <l>Once more forgiveneſs.</l>
                  <stage>(She kneels)</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Will this ſerve <hi>Evanthe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>(<hi>He raiſes and kiſſes</hi> her.)</stage>
                  <l>And this my Love, thou art all happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Man is a lump of earth, the beſt Man ſpiritleſs,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a Woman, all our lives and actions,</l>
                  <l>But counterfeits in Arras to ſuch virtue.</l>
                  <l>But did he tell no more?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <p>More than I then believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d or ever ſhall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Now we are both of one mind, lets be happy.</l>
                  <l>I am no more a wanting man <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy warm embraces ſhall diſſolve that impotence,</l>
                  <l>And my cold lye ſhall vaniſh with thy kiſſes.</l>
                  <l>Ye hours of night be long, as when <hi>Alcmena</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lay by the luſty ſide of <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Keep back the day and hide his golden beams,</l>
                  <l>Where the chaſt watchful morning may not find 'em.</l>
                  <l>Old doting <hi>Tython,</hi> hold <hi>Aurora</hi> faſt,</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106256:23"/>
                  <l>And tho ſhe bluſh, the day break from her cheeks,</l>
                  <l>Conceal her ſtill; thou heavy wain ſtand ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And ſtop the quicker revolutions;</l>
                  <l>Or if the day muſt come to ſpoil our happineſs</l>
                  <l>Thou envious Sun peep not upon our pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>Thou that all Lovers Curſe be far off from us.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Piſano <hi>with Guards.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let's to bed, and this night in all Joys</l>
                  <l>And chaſt deſires—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay I muſt part you both, it is the King's Command.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! this from thee, <hi>Piſano;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou once waſt honeſt, what can honour then,</l>
                  <l>And friendſhip too conſpire againſt <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My honour'd Lord, you'll find me ſtill your Friend,</l>
                  <l>Bear off the Lady, and uſe her with all nobleneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> with <hi>Evanthe.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Alphonſo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Call up the Sun, and tell him I wait for him.</l>
                  <l>He promis'd more I fear than he'll perform,</l>
                  <l>To find three men, that are not errant Traitors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there a myſtery beyond what I've ſuffer'd?</l>
                  <l>Yet witneſs Heav'n, this adds to my afflictions,</l>
                  <l>How do you my good Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Why very well.</l>
                  <l>Who are you? For I'm ſure I do not know you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Not know me,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>How is't poſſible I ſhou'd?</l>
                  <l>I well remember I had a foſter Brother,</l>
                  <l>A noble youth, my Father call'd <hi>Valerio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But what of that? I know you are not he.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi> was made up of nobleneſs,</l>
                  <l>Maſter of all thoſe humane excellencies,</l>
                  <l>That make Men equal to th'all perfect Gods;</l>
                  <l>His forward vertues ſhot him up to Man,</l>
                  <l>E're others cou'd attain to a youth's ſtrength.</l>
                  <l>He was ſo perfect as if heaven had ſent him,</l>
                  <l>To witneſs to the world the worth of humane nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> am I ſure I hear you!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>He wore a ſoul ſo full of manly greatneſs,</l>
                  <l>As wou'd have brook t a ſcepter'd Devil ſooner.</l>
                  <l>Than uſurpation, or a lawleſs Tyrant,</l>
                  <l>And e're he wou'd have ſpent thoſe precious hours,</l>
                  <l>That pitying fate had liberally conſign'd,</l>
                  <l>For the redemption of his wretched Country,</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106256:24"/>
                  <l>In the endearments of a fruitleſs paſſion,</l>
                  <l>He wou'd have ſold himſelf to ſlavery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Go on, my Lord, for tho in your reproofs</l>
                  <l>Y' appear as dreadful as an angry God,</l>
                  <l>Y' have turn'd the ſtream of my o erflowing griefs,</l>
                  <l>And ſilenc'd all the Tumults of my Soul.</l>
                  <l>Go on, for whilſt you ſpeak, my buſie ſorrows,</l>
                  <l>Tho they exceed the tortures of the damn'd,</l>
                  <l>As if another <hi>Orpheus</hi> came to charm 'em,</l>
                  <l>Are calm, and gently ſink down into peace.</l>
                  <l>Here on my knees ſilent as death I'm fix't,</l>
                  <l>And liſten to the charge of awful vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>He was ſo true a lover of his Country,</l>
                  <l>That for her ſake he would have given up</l>
                  <l>His life, and with it his Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s happineſs,</l>
                  <l>But not have ſold it like a trading Slave,</l>
                  <l>For the enjoyments of a ſhort-lif'd pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>He dar'd meet death with an undaunted courage,</l>
                  <l>On any ſcore, but from the Hangman's hand:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O all ye Gods, can I believe my ſenſes?</l>
                  <l>Or do I dream? 'tis real; for my joys</l>
                  <l>Exceed the tranſports of deluded fancy,</l>
                  <l>But ſay, my Lord, O tell me I adjure ye,</l>
                  <l>What kinder power, in pity of our ſufferings,</l>
                  <l>When you was loſt and dead to all our hopes,</l>
                  <l>Has thus reſtor'd ye to your bleeding <hi>Naples?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Vain man, 'tis thou art dead and not <hi>Alphonſo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That vigorous heat that fir'd thy active Youth,</l>
                  <l>And drew the hopes of all good men unto thee,</l>
                  <l>Lies quite extinct, and now thou art no more,</l>
                  <l>Than the faint ſhadow of <hi>Valerio</hi>'s greatneſs.</l>
                  <l>Ye Gods, that man, the Lord of your Creation,</l>
                  <l>The perfect image of your heavenly forms,</l>
                  <l>Shou'd own the weakneſs of the vileſt Beaſt,</l>
                  <l>And vertue, given us as a faithful guide</l>
                  <l>To lead us ſafe through a tempeſtuous Sea,</l>
                  <l>Shou'd yield to every wave that dares oppoſe it!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I own all you can charge me with,</l>
                  <l>And in an humble ſenſe of my own vileneſs,</l>
                  <l>I crawl thus low, to kiſs your ſacred feet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi> owns you have ſearch't him to the quick,</l>
                  <l>And laid his ſoul ſo open to her ſelf,</l>
                  <l>That now aſham'd of her own nakedneſs,</l>
                  <l>Dares not erect her head to view, and worſhip,</l>
                  <l>The Godlike beams of your ſeverer vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106256:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me then raiſe her up to her own greatneſs,</l>
                  <l>And heal her with the charms of holy Friendſhip,</l>
                  <l>Here let me fix her, honours ſacred twin,</l>
                  <l>And breath the ſweets of manly love upon her.</l>
                  <l>O my <hi>Valerio,</hi> we have been both to blame,</l>
                  <l>The hours of youth, that ſhou'd have been employ'd,</l>
                  <l>In the purſuit of never dying glory,</l>
                  <l>And ſpent i'th' ſervice of our wretched Country,</l>
                  <l>We have like headleſs Prodigals permitted</l>
                  <l>To glide as gentle waters unobſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſay, O teach me how to anſwer.</l>
                  <l>Thoughts crowd on thoughts, and preſs upon my Tongue,</l>
                  <l>Which cannot ſpeak the language of my Heart.</l>
                  <l>Only thus much, I fling off all my duty</l>
                  <l>To your dead Brother, for he is dead to goodneſs,</l>
                  <l>And to the living hopes of brave <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The noble heir of Nature and of Honour,</l>
                  <l>I faſten my Allegiance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Once more <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Since thou art ſo nobly faſhion'd to my Arms</l>
                  <l>Th'art wellcome, thus and thus I preſs thee to me,</l>
                  <l>Wiſh we might grow ſo fix't, ſo link't together,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Fredericks</hi> power might ſtrive in vain to part us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there on Earth that power that can divide us?</l>
                  <l>That life my love ſo fondly gave away,</l>
                  <l>Honour recalls: for you I will preſerve it,</l>
                  <l>That cou'd not for my ſelf. I'm yours, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi>'s yours, and to ſecure me ſo,</l>
                  <l>Witneſs ye Gods <hi>Valerio</hi> quits the world,</l>
                  <l>All but his love, and if my Lord commands it,</l>
                  <l>I'll quit that too; <hi>Evanthe</hi> ſhall be quitted,</l>
                  <l>And thrown off from me, that I may with eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Enter the liſt, and run the race of glory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou waſt born to recall baniſht vertue;</l>
                  <l>And fix her on her Throne; no, my <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mayſt thou be ever bleſt in thy <hi>Evanthe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Live both the happy Stars of love and honour,</l>
                  <l>Two lights to guide us in this darker Age.</l>
                  <l>But liſten now to what I ſhall unfold,</l>
                  <l>This afternoon, the Tyrant has determin'd</l>
                  <l>To try if fear will work upon <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And win her to compliance, if to ſave,</l>
                  <l>Thy much lov'd life ſhe will give up her honour;</l>
                  <l>If that will not prevail, 'tis then reſolv'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106256:25"/>
                  <l>By force to drag her to his impious luſt.</l>
                  <l>Now canſt thou tamely ſee a Virgin wrong'd,</l>
                  <l>And not be touch't with the indignity,</l>
                  <l>Perceive thy Wife forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to a Tyrant's bed,</l>
                  <l>And feel no love within to do her Juſtice?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Why asks my Lord, by heaven I'd rather ſee her</l>
                  <l>Drag'd to a bloody Altar, and there fall</l>
                  <l>A Sacrifice to Devils.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>I do believe thee,</l>
                  <l>And that thou woud'ſt be foremoſt to prevent it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d do't alone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>I grant it if no Friends</l>
                  <l>Can be found out to joyn i'th' undertaking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>There can be none;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>There are already hundreds</l>
                  <l>All arm'd, ev'n now the fatal Sword is drawn,</l>
                  <l>That muſt ere night diſpatch the bloody Tyrant.</l>
                  <l>Suſpend thy wonder, and be like thy ſelf.</l>
                  <l>O I cou'd tell thee ſuch a diſmal ſtory</l>
                  <l>As wou'd add fuel, to thy enraged ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>Tho' they boil'd higher than <hi>Alcides</hi> did,</l>
                  <l>When on his back he wore th' envenom'd Shirt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O you have given new life to all my wiſhes!</l>
                  <l>Is there, and ſhall we once again behold</l>
                  <l>A lawful Monarch ſeated on our Throne.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee the Genius of our State</l>
                  <l>Reſume with joy her once abandon'd Seat,</l>
                  <l>Vertue returns, and injur'd Truth once more</l>
                  <l>Do's happy <hi>Naples</hi> to her ſelf reſtore,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the aſſembl'd Gods reſolve to bleſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s Reign with a perpetual Peace.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT. V. Scene 1ſt.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi> Enter</hi> Frederick <hi>and</hi> Sorano.</stage>
               <stage>A Chair ſet on.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>BUT are you ſure the Poyſon's Mortal?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Above the help of Phyſick;</l>
                  <l>Some two hours hence we ſhall have ſuch a bawling,</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106256:25"/>
                  <l>And roaring up and down for <hi>Aqua Vitae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I've ſent him that will make a bonefire in his belly,</l>
                  <l>If he recover it, there is no heat in Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>But was my Mother eaſie of belief?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>At firſt indeed ſhe did miſtruſt my kindneſs,</l>
                  <l>And gravely told me old experienc't minds</l>
                  <l>Were not ſo quickly caught with guilt hypocriſie,</l>
                  <l>Then Sir I wept, and bid her as ſhe was honourable,</l>
                  <l>Not add more Hell to my afflicted ſoul;</l>
                  <l>Told her I had caſt off thoſe glorious favours</l>
                  <l>Of ſound and honour, wealth and promiſes,</l>
                  <l>Your wanton pleaſures had flung on my weakneſs;</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd to ſerve my Countries cauſe and vertues,</l>
                  <l>Poorly and honeſtly, and redeem my ruins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>I gueſs the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I produc'd the Viol,</l>
                  <l>Which at the price of half my wealth I bought,</l>
                  <l>So I poſſeſt her, from an antient Jew,</l>
                  <l>A learned Scholar, and a rare Phyſician:</l>
                  <l>And, ſhe not dreaming of an Antidote,</l>
                  <l>I freely drank an health unto <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay advis'd her to pledge it; if ſhe do's, Sir,</l>
                  <l>She'll find enough for both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>May both die then;</l>
                  <l>Now, my <hi>Sorano,</hi> we ſhall live indeed;</l>
                  <l>Methinks already I am mounted higher,</l>
                  <l>And with contempt look on the inferior world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt be ſpeedy, Sir, with this <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till he is cold i'th' Grave you are not ſafe;</l>
                  <l>There are ſome Lords, that buz about the Court,</l>
                  <l>And pry into our actions, they are ſuch</l>
                  <l>The fooliſh people call their Countries honours,</l>
                  <l>As if they were the Patterns of the Kingdom:</l>
                  <l>He is their Head, and him they Idolize,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>He dies this Afternoon, unleſs ſhe yields:</l>
                  <l>And as for his adherents, to their ſhames,</l>
                  <l>Within this week I'll ſilence 'em, <hi>Sorano,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'll ſuffer no proud ſlaves to be about me,</l>
                  <l>That are not followers of my will, bridles, and curbs,</l>
                  <l>To the hard headed Commons that malign us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>Now you ſpeak like a King; as for <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſhe's perverſe, remove her Paramour,</l>
                  <l>And then her love to him, which made her deaf</l>
                  <l>To all you cou'd propoſe, muſt periſh with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:106256:26"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt command in all; but, O <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I haſten on the wings of love to meet thee,</l>
                  <l>And die within thy Arms; were ſhe but kind</l>
                  <l>As ſhe is beautiful — but that wou'd be</l>
                  <l>Too great a happineſs. Her cruel pride</l>
                  <l>May for ſome time, like the reſiſtleſs tide,</l>
                  <l>My hopes on Rocks, and deſperate Quickſands throw;</l>
                  <l>The Heavens may rage above, and the Seas ſwell below,</l>
                  <l>But the bold Pilates Love,</l>
                  <l>Securily touches the forbidden ſtrand,</l>
                  <l>And gently throws me on the promis'd Land.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>To thee 'twill prove a wandering Fairy land,</l>
                  <l>Enjoy <hi>Evanthe?</hi> no, it was enough</l>
                  <l>That I indulg'd him with a Crown and Scepter,</l>
                  <l>But can't yield up my love ſo tamely to him,</l>
                  <l>He comes, and love plays in his Fiery eyes,</l>
                  <l>But darts his beams on an ungrateful ſoil;</l>
                  <l>Surely fate's buſie, and the kinder Stars</l>
                  <l>Are in conjunction to make good <hi>my hopes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Fr. <hi>and</hi> Evanthe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Can neither Power, Promiſe, Threats nor Tears,</l>
                  <l>Draw from your eyes one kind conſenting look,</l>
                  <l>To feed a Monarchs almoſt dying hopes?</l>
                  <l>Why wou'd you kill me with this cruelty,</l>
                  <l>This ſtubborn pride? look on me, fair <hi>Evanthe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not as a King, that might command thy will,</l>
                  <l>But as a Slave that muſt be govern'd by it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>You are a King, I wiſh I might ſay worthy</l>
                  <l>That love all honeſt men are bound to pay you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>O make me yours, and mold me as you pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>I own <hi>Evanthe,</hi> I'm made up of miſchiefs,</l>
                  <l>Have drawn the curſes of all good men on me.</l>
                  <l>But do not thou learn cruelty from me.</l>
                  <l>To heav'n we kneel for mercy, and obtain it.</l>
                  <l>To man we fly for Juſtice, and he gives it.</l>
                  <l>The ſenſeleſs Beaſts ſeem with relenting pity,</l>
                  <l>To joyn with us in our ſevereſt ſorrows.</l>
                  <l>Be like the Heavens, all ſoftneſs, tenderneſs,</l>
                  <l>The pride of nature, and the joy of life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord your power may force me to hear this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ever to comply with your deſires,</l>
                  <l>Or to be brought to love you wantonly,</l>
                  <l>Not all the honours you can throw upon me.</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106256:26"/>
                  <l>Shall e'er oblige me. I've a noble Husband,</l>
                  <l>And when I do forget him, or in thought</l>
                  <l>Wander from my obedience, then may I be</l>
                  <l>Sold up, and loſt to all thoſe lawleſs pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>That leave behind 'em nothing but diſhonour,</l>
                  <l>The unhappy Subjects of a late repentance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You have a Husband, but he dies this moment,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs you yield, and ſo redeem his life.</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd, come do not, do not wind</l>
                  <l>My anger to that height; it may conſume ye;</l>
                  <l>Yet I have mercy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Uſe it to your Bawds,</l>
                  <l>To me uſe cruelty, it beſt becomes you.</l>
                  <l>Thou art a King of Monſters, not of men,</l>
                  <l>And ſhortly wilt convert this land to Devils.</l>
                  <l>O were I but ſo powerfull to conſume thee!</l>
                  <l>My tongue with curſes I have arm'd againſt thee,</l>
                  <l>With Maiden curſes, that heav'n Crowns with horrors.</l>
                  <l>And cou'd my hands but hold the fire of heav'n,</l>
                  <l>Wrapt in the thunder that the Gods revenge with,</l>
                  <l>Then like ſtern Juſtice I wou'd fling it on thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Tho' ſhe's unexorable, ſtill I love,</l>
                  <l>And loving muſt enjoy. Thou ſtubborn Maid</l>
                  <l>I'll beg no more for what I can command.</l>
                  <l>I know I am a King and thou my ſlave,</l>
                  <l>And as a King I'll bodly ſeize my right,</l>
                  <l>I'll not delay my bliſs one Moment longer</l>
                  <l>Tho my dead Fathers Ghoſt ſhou'd riſe before me,</l>
                  <l>To ſhake my ſoul and fright me from my purpoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>Help, help, O help! is Providence aſleep</l>
                  <l>Or are the Gods deaf to a Virgins Prayers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>The Gods are Juſt, but proud oppreſſion hears not,</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Valerio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Tho' dreadfull Thunder ſhakes the frame of nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>How now, what boldneſs brought you hither, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Love and the duty of a faithfull Husband,</l>
                  <l>The duty of a Subject to his ſoveraign.</l>
                  <l>Here on my knees I do entreat you, Sir,</l>
                  <l>To render back what you with-hold unjuſtly;</l>
                  <l>Your Father was a kind, and generous Prince,</l>
                  <l>Your Brother th' Image of his Royal vertues,</l>
                  <l>Till ſubtle Poiſon rob'd him of his reaſon.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n you when firſt you ſeiz'd th' Imperial Crown</l>
                  <l>Promis'd the bleſſings of a gentle rule,</l>
                  <l>Till drunk with Pride, and arbitrary Power,</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:106256:27"/>
                  <l>Like a wild Boar too ſtrong to be with-held,</l>
                  <l>You broke the bounds of Nature, Law, Religion,</l>
                  <l>Reduc'd our Fruitfull once, and flouriſhing State</l>
                  <l>Into a miſerable, wild and deſert waſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir? who am I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not who you are,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould be <hi>Frederick,</hi> brave <hi>Brandino</hi>'s Son,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe reverend relicks, tho laid up in Peace,</l>
                  <l>Mourn in the Grave to think he ſhou'd beget,</l>
                  <l>And leave behind him ſuch an Helliſh Monſter.</l>
                  <l>You ſhou'd be —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What I am, a ſoveraign Prince,</l>
                  <l>And Maſter of thy Fate, Guards, ſeize the Traitor,</l>
                  <l>And ſee him dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold you miſtake your duty.</l>
                  <l>There ſtands the Traitor, Murderer, Parricide!</l>
                  <l>Tis not in words t' expreſs a guilt like thine,</l>
                  <l>Nor in all Hell, torments enough to puniſh it.</l>
                  <l>Nay frown not; tho' thy Eyes are Poiſonous,</l>
                  <l>As are thy hands, and Monſtrous as thy thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not kill me as thou didſt thy Father,</l>
                  <l>Thy innocent Brother, and thy noble Uncle.</l>
                  <l>If what I've utter'd is a falſhood, <hi>Frederick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Draw, if thou dareſt, thy ſelf the Sword of Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>And thruſt it home, to prove <hi>Valerio</hi> falſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Here then, I ll once be Executioner</l>
                  <l>To my own Vengeance and to ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Thy fatal Pride brag when thou comeſt below</l>
                  <l>Amongſt thy fellow ſhades, that <hi>Frederick</hi> kill'd thee</l>
                  <l>Thou arogant ſlave —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Alphonſo Cum Suis</hi> and <hi>Sorano.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold or you both ſhall die.</l>
                  <l>Unkind <hi>Valerio</hi> wou'd'ſt thou rob my Sword.</l>
                  <l>Of the only Juſtice my hopes ever aim'd at.</l>
                  <l>My Fathers Ghoſt wou'd ſtill walk unreveng'd,</l>
                  <l>If he ſhou'd fall by any hand but mine.</l>
                  <l>Put up for ſhame, hark to the Bell that Rings,</l>
                  <l>Hark, hark, Proud <hi>Frederick,</hi> that was King of miſcheif,</l>
                  <l>The Sun of all thy pomp is ſet and vaniſh't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>What do you ſhake, my Lord <hi>Sorano,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No ſpeedy miſchief to prevent this buſineſs,</l>
                  <l>No Bawdy meditation now to fly to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                  <l>O my beſt Lord let me with tears of Joy,</l>
                  <l>In theſe dear Arms ſigh out my thanks to Heav'n.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>ſo tamely caught! lock fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Pallace Gates.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:106256:27"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, Sir, we hear you, we have got the Keys,</l>
                  <l>And no doors here ſhall ſhut without our licence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <p>Treaſon, Treaſon!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>You can bawl well,</l>
                  <l>But we have found the Traitor in your ſhape, Sir,</l>
                  <l>And mean to keep him faſt, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> King <hi>Alphonſo!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>Long live <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> King of us and <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Turn, if thou dareſt look nature in the face,</l>
                  <l>Turn, <hi>Frederick,</hi> and boldly meet my Sword,</l>
                  <l>For till the Royal throne by thee polluted</l>
                  <l>And dawb'd with innocent blood, is purg'd by thine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alphonſo</hi> cannot, dares not, be a King;</l>
                  <l>And tho' thou well deſerv'ſt the Hangman's hand,</l>
                  <l>I'le be my ſelf the Miniſter of Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I han't forgot thou once waſt noble;</l>
                  <l>If thou prevail'ſt thou ſtill maiſt be a King,</l>
                  <l>Think Heav'n looks down as witneſs of our Combat,</l>
                  <l>And will refix the Crown o'th' Victors Head:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Now thou art brave and in thy nobleneſs</l>
                  <l>My Guilty Soul beholds her own diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>I do confeſs my unbounded ſins, but find</l>
                  <l>My heart too ſtubborn for a true repentance;</l>
                  <l>What I by treachery purchas'd hitherto</l>
                  <l>I have maintain'd by force; and know, <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frederick</hi> with greater pleaſure draws his Sword</l>
                  <l>In this diſpute, than if he was to ſtruggle</l>
                  <l>For a third Portion of the Univerſe.</l>
                  <l>Heav'n be thy Umpire, I to Hell appeal,</l>
                  <l>If there be either, for as yet I know not;</l>
                  <l>Let but my Sword be conſtant to my purpoſe,</l>
                  <l>I'll call no other God to my aſſiſtance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou Helliſh fury ſent by angry Heav'n</l>
                  <l>To ſcourge this bleeding Nation for her ſins.</l>
                  <l>Think on the miſcheifs thou haſt thrown upon her,</l>
                  <l>The ſighs and tears of injur'd innocence,</l>
                  <l>And curſes th' haſt entail'd upon Poſterity,</l>
                  <l>That after death will follow, and torment</l>
                  <l>Thy guilty aſhes in their reſtleſs Urn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace or I ſhall miſtruſt thy bravery.</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou to fright me with ſuch tales as theſe?</l>
                  <l>If thy Sword proves as Idle as thy Tongue,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall begin to doubt if one Womb bore us both.</l>
                  <l>Come on, methinks I am now proud to ſee thee</l>
                  <l>A match fit for my Sword, and not that ſtupid</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:106256:28"/>
                  <l>Senſeleſs <hi>Alphonſo</hi> I have often thought thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <p>Come then ſince th'art ſo brave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord <hi>Alphonſo</hi>—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold on the forfeit of your lives I charge you,</l>
                  <l>That Sword that is not ſheath'd is drawn on me.</l>
                  <l>So nobly is my cauſe born out with Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>That I require no aids but thoſe of Heav'n.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>O that th' whole World were ſummon'd to behold</l>
                  <l>Two rival-Brothers tugging for an Empire,</l>
                  <l>And with an Univerſal ſhout applaud the Victor.</l>
                  <l>Come on, we trifle, whilſt the eager Croud;</l>
                  <l>Divided in their wiſhes, grow impatient</l>
                  <l>Till Victory has taught 'em whom t' obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus then I meet thee tho' my Mother bore thee.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Wounds</hi> Fred.</stage>
                  <l>There lie, and maiſt thou be forgot for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I feel the hand of fate upon me, whilſt my Eyes</l>
                  <l>Labour in death, and view, brimfull of horror,</l>
                  <l>A diſmall proſpect of Eternal woe.</l>
                  <l>I now repent me of my cruelties,</l>
                  <l>And feel within my Soul the ſmarts already.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I bequeath thee all thoſe honours</l>
                  <l>I have uſurpt; but know thou can'ſt not long</l>
                  <l>Enjoy them, for thou haſt already drunk</l>
                  <l>Thy paſsport to the other world. But O</l>
                  <l>In death I do entreat thee to forgive me.</l>
                  <l>Hide not the noble nature of a Brother.</l>
                  <l>The pity of a friend from my afflictions.</l>
                  <l>I've liv'd a wicked life, but now—am nothing.</l>
                  <stage>Dies.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Tho' he was wicked, ſtill he was my Brother,</l>
                  <l>And ſhou'd have liv'd, 'till Humble penitence</l>
                  <l>Had caſt the load off of his wantonneſs.</l>
                  <l>I think he ſaid I ſhou'd not long ſurvive him.</l>
                  <l>Sure fate ſpoke in him, for I feel already</l>
                  <l>Convulſive heats ſhooting through every vein,</l>
                  <l>Struggling for freedom in their narrow priſon.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Queen Mother.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. Mother,</speaker>
                  <l>Where is my Son, O bear me to <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Son <hi>Alphonſo!</hi> the great pains I felt</l>
                  <l>When firſt thou ſaw'ſt the light, were ſofteſt pleaſures</l>
                  <l>Compar'd to thoſe that rack my body now,</l>
                  <l>Which thou muſt feel e're thou lieſt down in Peace.</l>
                  <l>Millions of horrors, labours, all diſeaſes,</l>
                  <l>Deſpairs and Plagues the hot Sun ever breeds</l>
                  <l>Are trifles to the torments I endure:</l>
                  <l>The ſhadows of the pains thy Mother feels.</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:106256:28"/>
                  <l>O damn'd deceitfull Helliſh Poiſonous Villain!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaith my Mother: O my mind miſgives me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. Mother,</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art Poiſon'd Son, by thy own Mother Poiſon'd</l>
                  <l>Who has her ſelf drunk of the deadly draught,</l>
                  <l>To lead thee to the Manſions of the bleſſed.</l>
                  <l>Give me more Air, let inundations flow</l>
                  <l>Colder than Snow upon the Scythian Mountains.</l>
                  <l>O I'm all fire, <hi>Sorano</hi> is the Villain,</l>
                  <l>Let infinite tortures, ſuch as thoſe I feel,</l>
                  <l>Light on his Head, and then I ſhall die pleas'd.</l>
                  <stage>Dies.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Now, my <hi>Valerio,</hi> where are all my hopes,</l>
                  <l>Ye Gods—but ſtill you muſt be mercifull</l>
                  <l>Tho' man can't ſearch the ways of Providence,</l>
                  <l>But at a diſtance views you in your works.</l>
                  <l>O Mournfull Triumph, fatal Victory!</l>
                  <l>The earth is now <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s only Throne</l>
                  <l>And that in death I'll keep: I feel him coming,</l>
                  <l>Or am I dead already? no death's cold:</l>
                  <l>But I'm all fire, fire, the raging Dog-ſtar</l>
                  <l>Reigns in my blood. O which way ſhall I turn me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſt thee, <hi>Piſano,</hi> fly for the Phyſicians;</l>
                  <l>Tell 'em rewards exceeding all their wiſhes</l>
                  <l>Shall Crown their cares if they'll reſtore back to us</l>
                  <l>This one lov'd life. Look up, my honour'd Lord,</l>
                  <l>See willing nations courting ye to live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me more Air, Air, more Air, blow, blow;</l>
                  <l>Open thou Eaſtern gate and blow upon me,</l>
                  <l>Diſtill thy cold dews, O thou Icy Moon,</l>
                  <l>And rivers run through my afflicted ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aetna</hi> and all his flames burn in my Head;</l>
                  <l>Fling me into the <hi>Ocean</hi> or I periſh.</l>
                  <l>Dig, dig, dig 'till the ſprings fly up,</l>
                  <l>The cold, cold ſprings that I may leap into 'em,</l>
                  <l>And bath my ſcorch'd limbs in their purling pleaſures.</l>
                  <l>O ſhoot me up into the higher region</l>
                  <l>Where Treaſures of delicious ſnow are nouriſh'd</l>
                  <l>And banquets of ſweet hail.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte there, ſhut all the Palace gates and ſeize that Villain;</l>
                  <l>Tortures exceeding thoſe o'th' damn'd in Hell</l>
                  <l>Shall be thy lot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare your utmoſt malice</l>
                  <l>There I'm reveng'd, and in that thought rejoyce.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Go bear him to the rack. Was ever day like this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>What will you ſacrifice me?</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106256:29"/>
                  <l>Upon the Altar lay my willing body</l>
                  <l>And pile your wood up, fling your holy incenſe,</l>
                  <l>And as I turn me, you ſhall ſee all flame,</l>
                  <l>Conſuming flame, ſtand off me or y'are aſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>help me to raiſe him, Sirs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Bring hither Charity and let me hug her,</l>
                  <l>They ſay ſhe's cold,</l>
                  <l>Infinite cold devotion cannot warm her.</l>
                  <l>Draw me a River of falſe Lovers tears</l>
                  <l>Clean through my breaſt they are dull, cold and forgetfull;</l>
                  <l>And will give eaſe!</l>
                  <l>Let Virgins ſigh upon me,</l>
                  <l>Forſaken ſouls, their ſighs are precious</l>
                  <l>Let 'em all ſigh, O Hell, Hell, Hell, O horror.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſcalding ſweats he has</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>I am inclos'd in all conſuming flames.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Phaton</hi> let me fly, let me fly, give me room</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the cold bear and the raging Lyon,</l>
                  <l>Lyes my ſafe way. O for a Cake of Ice now,</l>
                  <l>To clap upon my heart to comfort me.</l>
                  <l>Decrepid Winter hang upon my ſhoulders,</l>
                  <l>And let wear thy frozen Iſicles</l>
                  <l>Like Jewels round about my head to cool me,</l>
                  <l>My eyes burn out and ſink into their ſockets,</l>
                  <l>And my infected brain like brimſtone boils,</l>
                  <l>I live in Hell and ſeveral furies Vex me,</l>
                  <l>O carry me where no Sun ever ſhow'd yet</l>
                  <l>A face of comfort, where the Earth is Chryſtal,</l>
                  <l>Never to be diſſolv'd, where naught inhabits</l>
                  <l>But night and cold, and nipping Froſt and Winds.</l>
                  <l>That cut the ſtubborn rocks and make 'em ſhiver.</l>
                  <l>Set me there Friends I feel it, and am happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>There broke the noble heart I ſhou'd follow him</l>
                  <l>In death did not the charms of love recall me;</l>
                  <l>Bear in th' unhappy relicks and prepare</l>
                  <l>Noble interments worthy their great lives.</l>
                  <l>For me I have ſome right to the ſucceſſion</l>
                  <l>Which in a general Aſſembly I'll make known.</l>
                  <l>Death finds the Monarch ſeated on his Throne</l>
                  <l>With as much eaſe as th' humble Cottager:</l>
                  <l>But Proud unthinking men are taught too late,</l>
                  <l>No power can ſave 'em from the hand of fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
